女士们  先生们
Ladies and gentlemen!
我们在苏联的莫斯科
We're in Moscow,in the Soviet Union.
这肯定是拳击史上最多人观看的一场比赛
This promises to be the most-watched event in boxing history.
《洛奇5》
我要击败你
I must break you.
到右边去
Throw your right!
他把洛奇困在角落
He will not let him out of that corner.
洛奇
Rocky!
洛奇身陷困境
Rocky Balboa is in serious trouble.
他毫无招架之力
He's getting killed!
德拉戈挥拳猛击洛奇
Drago continuing to punish Rocky Balboa.
- 不痛  - 不痛
- No pain! - No pain.
洛奇惨遭修理  洛奇受伤了
Rocky's been hit with bombs. Rocky's hurt!
德拉戈一记右拳把洛奇打得倒飞15英尺
The right hand from Drago sends Rocky Balboa 15 feet across the ring.
拳王被击倒了
The champ is down.
洛奇  快起来
Rocky,Get up!
目前的战况是一面倒
It's been a one-sided fight so far.
德拉戈一记猛烈的右拳把洛奇打得头昏脑胀
Drago throws a hard right hand and stuns Rocky Balboa!
再不停止比赛就要出人命了
They might have to stop this one before somebody gets killed.
洛奇惨遭一轮重拳  他已欲振乏力
Rocky taking punishment! He's completely exhausted.
洛奇又被一记右钩拳击倒在地
Balboa goes down again from a right hand!
重拳有如排山倒海  惊人的意志力
Lethal punch after punch. Amazing willpower!
洛奇到目前还招架得住德拉戈的每一拳
Rocky Balboa has taken all of Drago's best punches.
他已经是血流满面
He's cut and bleeding.
到底是怎么回事?
What's happening out there?
- 我看见三个影子  - 打中间那个影子
- I see three of him out there. - Hit the one in the middle.
对  打中间那个
Right! Hit the one in the middle!
- 俄国选手流血了  - 打倒他
- The Russian's cut! - Kill him!
像摔角手般扭倒在地  简直是市井小民的打法
To the ground like a wrestler! It's a gutter war.
莫斯科的拳赛完全不设限
No holds barred in Moscow!
用尽你的全力  使出浑身解数
All your strength,power. Everything you've got.
关乎你一生前途
This is your whole life!
洛奇一记右钩拳
A good right hand by Rocky Balboa!
洛奇赢得不可能的比赛
Rocky Balboa has done the impossible!
洛奇...
Rocky! Rocky!
我从未见过这种场面
I never saw nothing like it.
你以拳王的精神坚持到底  你和大家都无比光荣
You came through like the champ you are. Did yourself and everybody proud.
尤其是阿波罗
Especially Apollo!
- 汤尼  - 怎么了  宝贝  你需要什么?
- Yo,Tony. - What is it,baby? What do you need?
叫艾莉来
Get Adrian.
大家在外面还好吧
How's everybody doing out there?
大家都很好
Oh. Everything's okay.
怎么了?
What's wrong?
还记得米克说过当年他出赛时
Remember when Mick said when he was fightin'...
有时候出力过猛
sometimes he'd fight so hard...
感觉就好像...五脏六腑全散掉了
that he was thinking he broke somethin' inside...
他好像快死了一样
and he was gonna die?
他说这时候就像天使在召唤他
That's what he said when the angels was pullin' on him.
你吓坏我了
Rocky,you're scaring me.
怎么了?
What's wrong?
艾莉  我不能
Adrian,I can't.
不能什么?
Can't what?
我...我不能停止我的双手颤动
I...I can't stop my hands from shaking.
- 以前从没这样子  - 你必须要看医生
- I never felt this thing. - We've gotta see a doctor.
- 不  我只想回家  - 回家?
- No. No,I just wanna go home. - Home?
- 对  - 不看医生吗?
- Yeah. - Not see a doctor?
我只是累了  我想回家  米克
I'm just tired. I just wanna go home,Mick.
我只是累了
I'm just tired.
我只想回家 好吗?
I just wanna go home,okay?
- 艾莉  孩子呢?  - 我不知道
- Adrian,where's the kid? - I don't know.
我没看见孩子  他在哪里?  他不在这里吗?
I don't see the kid. Where's the kid? Ain't he here?
爸...
Dad! Dad!
他在这  小拳王  你好吗
There he is! Hey,Slugger! How you doin'?
向你妈问候
Say hi to your mom.
- 忘了叫我吗?  - 保罗叔叔  你好
- I'm forgotten now? - Hi,Uncle Paulie.
- 你感觉怎么样?  - 身上还有几个伤口  学校还好吗
- Dad,how you feeling? - I got a few dents. How's school?
- 我上荣誉榜了  - 很棒
- I made the honor roll. - Beautiful!
我是希拉·唐丝  安全人员
I'm Sheila Downs,Airport Security.
请跟我来  记者会正在等你
Welcome. There's a press reception.
洛奇  你对俄国民众感觉如何?
Rocky,how did you feel about the Russian people in general?
很好  他们都很友善
Very good. They was great people.
我听不懂俄语
I didn't understand what they was speaking...
但是我明白他们的意思
but I understood what they was meaning.
- 洛奇太太  你学了几句俄语吧?  - 我有没有学俄语?
- Mrs. Balboa,did you learn any Russian? - Did I learn Russian?
她说伏特加很流畅
She got fluent in vodka.
洛奇  听说你比赛后身体不适
There are rumors of physical complications after the fight.
- 身体不适?  - 不
- Complications? - No!
这些只是谣传  他身体好的很
Those were rumors. He's in perfect physical condition.
我有个问题  美国医学协会最近建议禁止举行拳赛
Rocky,the American Medical Association recommended boxing be banned.
- 你同意他们的看法吗?  - 是的
- Do you agree with the doctors? - Yeah.
绝对同意  我认为医生不该参加拳赛
Absolutely. I think that doctors should never fight.
拳王  你答得太妙了  没错
That was a beautiful answer,champ! That's right.
医生应该远离拳击场  更不该比赛
Doctors should stay out of the ring forever,and never fight.
洛奇·巴尔博亚  最幽默的拳王
Rocky Balboa,the funkiest champion ever.
美国的洛奇·巴尔博亚  你好吗
American's own Rocky Balboa. How are you?
我是乔治·华盛顿·杜克  卓越的拳赛赞助者...
George Washington Duke here. Promoter extraordinaire...
欢迎回国  洛奇  全美及全苏联的拳王
welcoming back Rocky Balboa,champion of all the Americans and Russians!
我现在想先拉开话题  在媒体面前提出一项提议
I would like to digress and pose an interesting proposition to the media.
全市的居民...
Everyone in this city...
以及体育界的人士都知道我在国内...
and in sports knows my reputation for promoting...
曾主办无数精彩的比赛
some of the finest extravaganzas in this country.
所以趁新闻界都在场时  我郑重请求洛奇·巴尔博亚...
So,with the press present,I'd like to ask you,Rocky Balboa...
你是个灿烂  桀骜不驯的运动员
to be the flamboyant,rambunctious sportsman we know you can be...
给尤尼·肯恩这位年轻人
and give this man here,Union Cane,a chance to challenge you...
与你争夺世界重量级拳王的机会
for the Heavyweight Championship of the World.
巴尔博亚  我要夺走你的一切
Balboa,I want the opportunity to take what you got.
时机不对吧?  他才刚下飞机
Isn't this bad timing to present a challenger? He just got off the plane!
时机是生活的要素  各位先生女士
Timing is the essence of life,gentlemen and ladies.
我手上这纸合约
What I have on this paper is the largest guarantee...
提供的是世上最优渥的机会
ever offered to a champion on this planet!
我说的是  在日本举办规模最大的国际拳赛
I'm talking about a fantastic international extravaganza to be held...
称为"放手一搏在东京"
in Japan called "Lettin' It Go in Tokyo."
只有在美国  我们这种人才有机会
People,ain't it incredible that only in America...
脱离压迫  脱离贫穷
could people like us rise from oppression,from poverty...
携手参加国际性大赛
to join hands in this international event?
- 只有在美国  - 对不起
- Excuse me. - Only in America!
对不起  我先生退休了  他不想再证明什么了
My husband is retired. He has nothing more to prove.
等一下  洛奇  你不认为有责任
Wait a minute! Rocky,don't you consider this a public responsibility...
尽快回应
to respond now rather than later?
回应公众
Respond to the people.
难道这不是一个现在就要回答的专业问题吗?
Isn't this a question of professionalism to talk about it now,not later?
不介意等我康复吗?
You mind if I heal first?
你的伤不够看  我的拳头更厉害
The whippin' you got ain't nothin' like what I got here for you.
你是什么意思?
What in the hell does this all mean?
不 这样的回答不够  我现在就要知道
That isn't enough. We gotta hear now.
我还要考虑一下
I got to think about that.
总之  这趟旅行非常愉快
Anyway,the flight over was really nice.
我们还要更多答案
Guys,we need more.
艾莉  如果没有你  我表现不会这么好
Adrian,if you weren't with me,I never would have done as good.
你是我的挚爱  你永远都支持我  还有我的孩子
You're my Adrian. You're always there. And my kid.
有了你就好像重生一样
Having you is like bein' born all over again.
快点  你意下如何?  你究竟要不要退休?
Come on,what do you say? Are you gonna retire or not?
对不起  我想回家了
Excuse me. I'd like to go home.
- 你不给我们一些答案吗?  - 谢谢各位
- Give us something to write! - Thank you,I appreciate it.
不
No!
你放心  你一定能逼他出赛的  一定没问题的
Don't worry. You'll get him. You'll get him.
不  真的...
No,really,it's...
真的很棒  看看这个地方
Ah,yo! Look at this place!
我发誓再也不离开这里了  知道吗?
I swear I ain't never leavin' this place again,you know that?
想不想跳舞?
Hey,would you like to dance?
- 陪我跳支载誉归国舞?  - 别傻了  天气好冷
- How about a homecoming dance? - Don't be silly,it's cold.
小姐  我帮你暖身  来吧  跳支舞
I'll warm you up,young lady.
快点  音乐快结束了
Hurry up. The music's almost over.
- 你喜欢这首歌吗?  - 你该好好休息
- You're like the song... - You should rest.
- 我知道  - 我累了
- I know. - I'm tired. Come on.
或许我该带你上楼  好好亲热一番
Maybe I'll take you upstairs and violate you like a parking meter.
- 你得花钱  - 艾莉  你从哪里学会说黄色笑话的?
- Cost you a quarter. - Where'd you learn to talk dirty?
保罗叔?
Uncle Paulie?
你有没有觉得我爸怪怪的?
Did you notice something strange about Dad?
他只是受了点重伤罢了
He just took a few hard shots.
艾莉  你比我还会说笑话
I think you tell better jokes than me.
我是不是听见有人找老爸?  是你吗?
Did I hear somebody call for their old man? Did you do this?
孩子  该睡了  好吗
It's sleep time,okay?
爸  你知道睡觉时  骨头的成长会快三倍吗
Dad,did you know that your bones grow three times as fast during the night?
不知道  不过我听过一次  那是我吗
I didn't know that,but I heard somethin' like that once. Is that me?
- 对  就是你  - 太棒了
- Yeah,that's you. - Excellent!
真的是我?  我们去钓鱼的时候?
No,is that me? When we was fishin',right?
对  太美了  你看那座帐篷
That's beautiful! Look at the tent.
我记得鱼比较大
You know,the fish was a lot bigger,if I recall.
其实比这个还小
Actually,that was a lot smaller.
终归一句话  去睡吧
Anyway,come on. Hit the bed.
你也该注重身体健康
It's time for you to get healthy and everything.
太棒了  不知道你在哪里学的
This is great how you do this. I don't know where you learn this.
你画的真了不起
It is something how this thing comes out of your fingers.
我的天
Oh,my God!
她是谁
Who's this?
她是杜蓬夫人  我的法文老师
That's Madame Dupont,my French teacher.
真的?
Really?
是  她的确有法国人的味道
Yeah,she looks French. Sure.
别让你妈看见这个  因为她不太懂法语
I wouldn't show this to your mother 'cause she don't understand French.
天啊
My God.
最好盖起来  小拳王  该睡了
Better cover that one up. Champ,it's bedtime.
你知道吗?  我也懂些法语
Hey,you know what? I know some French talk.
敲敲门
Knock,knock.
- 哪位?  - 夫人
- Who's there? - Madame.
- 哪个夫人?  - 我的脚卡在门里
- Madame who? - My damn foot's caught in the door.
- 这是个老笑话了  - 那你想怎样?我在尽力
- That's an old joke! - What do you want from me? I'm trying.
我又不知道新的玩意儿
I don't know all the good things.
这是什么?
Whoa! What's this?
什么?
What?
我在你耳朵里找到的  俄国钱币
Look what I found in your ear. Russian money.
摇钱耳
Money ears!
好了  你得睡觉了
All right,listen,kid,you gotta get some sleep.
- 爸?  - 什么事?
- Dad? - Yeah?
你今天说有了我就像重生一样
Today when you said having me was like being born again?
- 怎么了?  - 是什么意思?
- Yeah? - What did you mean?
你知道...当你变得跟我从前一样
Well,you know,when you come up like I did and you got...
每日三餐不继  了解我的意思吗?
three square meals of zero a day,know what I mean?
生活有好坏两面
You got the "A" side of life and the "B" side of life.
我是在穷苦中长大  可是你不愁衣食
I'm like on the "B" side. But you got all the breaks.
所以当我见到你拥有我所没有的一切...
So when I see you having all these things that I didn't have...
我就好像见到自己
I live through your eyes.
我很喜欢  就好像一切又重生了
I enjoy it a little bit. It's like having it all over again.
非常好
That's nice.
看看我的脸  像不像浣熊?
Oh,hey,look at my face. Do I look like a raccoon?
有一点
A little bit.
像洛奇浣熊吗?
Like Rocky Raccoon?
对  有点像
A little bit.
- 是有一点像  - 真的?
- You do a little. - Really?
如果你认为我很惨  不妨去看看另一个人的下场
If you think I look bad,you oughta see the other guy's knuckles.
总之  晚安  孩子
Anyway,yo,good night. Okay,kid?
爸  很高兴你回家
Glad you're home.
谢谢  非常感激
Thanks. I appreciate it.
明天再玩  好吗?
We'll play tomorrow,okay?
或许你可以让我看看你的英文老师
Maybe you could show me your English teacher.
她也很火辣
She's pretty hot,too.
晚安  孩子
Good night,kid.
- 那不是你的钱  是洛奇的  - 你疯了吗?
- It wasn't your money. It was Rocky's. - You wanna be hysterical?
- 你害我们家当都没了  - 那是个错误
- You cost us everything. - It was a mistake.
- 你以为我知道这一切会发生吗?  - 不准你一走了之
- You think I thought this would happen? - Don't walk away from me!
你毁了我们的生活
You just gave up our life!
你还以为只是小错而已?
And you think it's like some stupid thing?
保罗  你知道你做了什么吗?  你可知严重性?
Paulie,do you know what you did? Do you know the seriousness of it?
- 我明白  - 那就回答我
- I understand it! - Then answer me!
我什么都了解  我懂
I understand the whole friggin' thing! I understand it!
你的会计是骗子  不是我  我做自认是对的事
Your accountant's a crook,not me! I did what I thought was right.
别怪我  我更想杀了那混蛋
Don't blame me! I wanna murder the bum worse than anybody!
艾莉  怎么了?
What's wrong?
瞧你做的好事  她要把烂摊子丢给我
Look what you've done now. She's dumping everything on me.
- 保罗 别怪在我头上  - 你到底做了什么?
- Paulie,don't turn this around on me. - What'd you do?
他竟把委任状交给会计师
He gave power of attorney to our accountant.
给他?  我什么都没给他  是他寄来一封信
"Gave"? I just didn't "gave" anything to nobody. He sent the letter!
他说我们要去俄国几个月
He says we're gonna be in Russia for a couple of months...
就要求洛奇签份税金展延申请书
and,"I need Rocky to sign a tax extension."
税金展延申请书  保罗  那是委任状
Tax extension! That was a power of attorney,Paulie!
他是个贼  我要喝酒
He's the thief! I need alcohol.
洛奇  老天有眼  我一毛钱也没偷
Rocky,on my eyes,I never stole a friggin' dime.
艾莉  怎么回事?
Adrian,what's happenin' here?
- 全完了  - 什么完了?
- It's gone. - What's gone?
我们的钱
The money.
一切全没了
Everything. It's all gone.
保罗叫你签字的文件不是税金展延申请书
The piece of paper Paulie had you sign wasn't a request for a tax extension.
而是一份空白委任状  支付给会计师
It was a blanket power of attorney,in favor of the accountant...
他正从事一些高价的房地产交易
who was involved in high-priced commercial real estate.
他以为可以趁你不注意
He thought he could flip it,take his profit...
周转一下再补回去
and have the money back before you knew it was gone.
不幸的是  你和在坐的所有人...
And unfortunately for you and everybody in this room...
他的交易没有成功
his deals fell through because
由于市场萎缩  你损失了数百万元
the market dried up,and you lost millions.
那么  你想说什么?  我一点办法都没有?
So,what are you saying? There ain't nothin' I can do?
办法很多  我已告他八项罪名
I'm doing plenty. I've filed eight criminal acts against him.
但是你有一大堆债务要还
But you've got tremendous debt payment on this property.
他六年没替你缴税  而且房屋贷款也还没有偿付
He didn't pay your tax returns,and the house mortgage hasn't been paid.
等一下  我们没有贷款  房屋贷款早就付清了
Wait. We didn't have a mortgage. Our house was fully paid for.
不是我这么说的
Then ask him.
显然不是  你们还差四十万贷款未缴
Apparently not. There's nearly $400,000 still outstanding.
目前唯一未负债的...
The only thing that's not encumbered is a gym...
是米克高米在1982年  遗留给你儿子的体育馆
that was willed to your son by a Mickey Goldmill in 1982.
你可以拍卖东西  还记得你拍过的广告吗?
You could sell some things. Remember those commercials you did?
我不是拍广告的  我是拳击手  靠双拳吃饭
I ain't no commercial kind of guy. I'm a fighter. It's what I do.
算了  我们也找不到人赞助
It's just as well. We couldn't get any sponsors.
在调查会计师的同时
With the investigation of the accountant out pops Rocky's criminal record...
会扯出洛奇从前讨债打人的案底
for assault in connection with loan sharking.
- 那是很久以前的事了  - 何不举办拳赛?
- That was long ago. - Why not a couple more fights?
以你的名气  很快就能解决困境
With your popularity now,you could be out of this in no time.
他要退休了
He's retiring.
拳赛是好办法
Fighting's the ticket.
我说他已经退休了  保罗  造成我们今天的局面全要怪你
I said,he's retired! Paulie,we're here because of you.
我才不接受这种说法  我认为我做的很聪明
I'm not takin' the heat for this. I thought I was doin' smart business.
你认为你很聪明?
You thought you did smart business?
- 都是你 - 我?
- You! - Me? What are you talking about me?
如果你要这样  我马上联络他
You should have known he was a thief,b
不  洛奇  求求你
No! Rocky,please!
我们不能那样下去  打几场拳赛就能解决问题了
We can't go down like that. A couple of fights,we're out of trouble.
你说过你不会
You said you wouldn't.
我什么都没说  你甘愿就这么认输吗?
I didn't say anything. Did we come this far to lose it?
- 你一定要看医生  - 我不需要医生  我需要主办人
- You have to see a doctor. - I don't need to. I need a promoter.
如果医生同意  我一定支持你
If the doctor says it's all right,I'll support you.
我一定得比赛  我有麻烦 一定要出赛
I've gotta fight. I got problems,I gotta fight.
你肯为我去看医生吗?
Will you do it for me?
好吧  为了你
All right,for you.
由于头部不断受到重击
Because of the continuous violent blows to the head,you've developed...
导致你的脑部产生拳手常见的膈腔薄膜穿孔
a condition particular to boxers called cavum septum pellucidum...
也就是脑膜中有洞
which is a hole in the membrane separating the ventricles.
脑部这个部位的表面神经也受伤
The brain's surface neurons in this area have also been traumatized.
医生  你说什么
Excuse me, Doctor.
简单地说  就是你的脑部已经受伤
Simply stated, it means you've suffered brain damage.
要多久才能痊愈?
How long until he recovers?
不可能复原
The effects are irreversible.
洛奇  你一定要退休
Oh,I... Rocky,you have to retire.
我不想退休
I don't wanna retire!
现在不是时候  更不是这里  绝不是在这间诊室
This ain't the time to retire. Not in here. Not in no office.
我刚打完一生最棒的拳赛  你知道吗?
I just fought the best fight of my life. I just did that.
我需要的是再多打几场
And all I need is a couple more.
不行  洛奇  你的脑伤很严重
No,Rocky! You suffered severe brain trauma!
- 他可能诊断错误  - 我不这么认为
- He could be wrong! Anybody could be! - I don't think he is.
他不是神  听好  艾莉  只有神不会出错
He ain't God! Adrian,only God ain't wrong.
洛奇  这是为了你好
Rocky,this is what's good for you.
我想再打几场轻松的拳赛
All I need's a couple easy ones,right?
你的状况根本拿不到执照
You can't get licensed in any state.
医生  他拿不到执照吧?
He can't get licensed anywhere?
没错
Correct.
洛奇  你爱我吗
Rocky,do you love me?
我爱你  为何这么问?
I love you. Why you ask that?
因为你爱一个人的话  你会和他们生活  为他们而活
Because if you love somebody,you live with them,you live for them.
你不会拿性命作赌注
You don't gamble with a life.
洛奇  我关心的不是钱而是你
I don't care about the money. It's you.
你才是最重要的
That's all that matters.
求求你  们过得去的  不会有事的
Please. We'll be okay. We'll be fine.
不要让人知道  别说出去好吗?
No one has to know,Doctor,right?
我们绝对守口如瓶
It'll be strictly confidential.
谢谢
Thank you.
还有没有人喊价?
May we hear the next bid,please?
没有了吗?
Are you done?
卖出给172号投标人
Sold.
接下来  各位女士先生  第46号拍卖品
Moving along,ladies and gentlemen,item number...
小鬼  机车已经卖出了
Hey,kid,the bike's been sold.
机车卖掉了  快下来  快点 Hey!
The bike's been sold. Get off the bike. Come on.
别担心  我们也失败过
Don't worry about it. We've been down before.
我会再弄回来的  我们一定要团结  好吗?
I'll get it all back. We just gotta stick together,right?
家族队
Home team.
说的对
Yeah,right.
走吧  米克常说没听到钟声比赛就不算结束
Come on. Mick used to say a fight ain't over till you heard the bell.
我们还没听到钟声
We ain't heard a bell yet,have we?
洛奇首次赢得拳王头衔的拳套
Rocky Balboa's boxing gloves from his first heavyweight championship fight.
还很合身
Hey,it still fits.
你为什么穿那件衣服?
Well,why you wearin' those clothes?
我在找东西时发现的  穿起来还蛮舒服的
I was just goin' through some stuff,found 'em,and they feel comfortable.
我在楼下一直找你
Well,I was lookin' for you downstairs.
- 拍卖会有点令人沮丧  - 对  我懂你的意思
- It's kind of depressing. - Yeah,I know what you mean.
这个怎么会在你耳朵?
Oh,what's this doin' in your ear?
- 天啊  - 你还记得这些吗?
- What? Oh,God! - Remember these?
对  你...
Yeah. You ...
我记得那天你帮我摘下眼镜
I remember when you took 'em off.
我和你的初吻  还记得吗
First time I ever kissed you,remember?
吻你
Kissed you.
艾莉  我想出去走一下
Adrian,I wanna go out for a little bit.
让心情好一点
Take a little walk,wanna feel better.
请你与孩子谈谈  因为他很难过
But could you talk to the kid,'cause he's really taking this hard.
- 当然  - 好的
- Sure. - Okay.
- 你要去哪里?  - 我不知道  大概去安迪酒吧
- Where are you goin'? - I thought I'd go to Andy's.
他是怎么搞砸的?
How did he blow it all?
米克  你好
How you doin',Mick?
出刺拳
Slip the jab!
- 出刺拳 - 听不懂吗?
- Slip the jab! - Slip thejab,will ya?
刺拳
Slip the jab!
对了 就是这样
That's right,that's it.
- 我可没听见钟声  - 好吧
- Hey,I didn't hear no bell! - Okay.
对了
All right.
对  出刺拳  对了  想像一下
That's right. Slip thejab. That's it! Mentalize!
想像有个蹩脚货在你前面
See that bum in front of you!
看见自己打得很好就能打赢
You see yourself doin' right and you do right.
漂亮  太棒了
That's pretty. That's very pretty.
时间到
Time!
洛奇  过来  天啊  你准备好了吧?
Come here,Rock. My God,you're ready,ain't you?
阿波罗会搞不清楚是什么击倒他
Apollo won't know what hit him.
你要像部推土机击倒他
You'll roll over him like an Italian bulldozer.
孩子  我知道你...
You know,kid,I know how you feel...
对这场比赛的感觉  因为我是过来人
about this fight that's comin' up because I was young once,too.
让我告诉你一件事
I tell you somethin'.
如果没有你
If you wasn't here...
今天我可能不会活着
gee,I probably wouldn't be alive today.
你在这里及所有的表现给了我...
The fact that you're here and doin' as well as you're doin' gives me...
你称它为什么?  活下去的动机?
What do you call it? A motivization to stay alive?
因为我认为人们不想活下去  就会死亡
'Cause I think that people die sometimes when they don't wanna live no more.
自然比人类想的还聪明
Nature's smarter than people think.
And nature is smarter than people think.
我们逐渐失去朋友  失去一切
Little by little,we lose our friends,we lose everything.
我们不断地失去  直到我们说...
We keep losin' and losin' till we say...
我活着究竟是为了什么?  我没有再活下去的理由
"What the hell am I livin' for? I got no reason to go on."
可是有了你  孩子  我就有理由了
But with you,kid,boy,I got a reason to go on.
我会好好活下去  我要看着你出人头地
And I'm gonna stay alive. And I will watch you make good.
- 我绝不离开你  - 我绝不离开你...
- And I'll never leave you. - And I'll never leave you...
直到你成功的一日
until that happens.
因为当我离开你时  你不仅知道如何打拳...
'Cause when I leave you,you'll not only know how to fight...
你还能在现实世界照顾自己  你明白吗?
you'll be able to take care of yourself outside the ring,too,is that okay?
好的
It's okay.
好的  我有个礼物送你 Okay.
Now I got a little gift for you.
- 米克...  - 等一下
- Aw,Mick... - Wait a minute now.
- 我什么也不需要  - 你看看  看到没?
- I don't need nothin'. - Look at this. See that?
这是我最心爱的东西
This here's the favorite thing that I have on this earth.
是洛奇·马西安诺给我的
And Rocky Marciano give me that.
你知道是什么吗?  他的袖扣
You know what it was? His cuff link.
现在我把它交给你
And now I'm givin' it to you.
它就像是...
And it's gotta be...
你肩膀上的天使  明白吗?
like an angel on your shoulder,see?
如果你受伤的时候  当你感觉快要倒下去
If you ever get hurt and feel that you're goin' down...
这位天使会在你耳边呼唤
this little angel is gonna whisper in your ear.
快起来  你这个混球
He's gonna say,"Get up,you son of a bitch...
因为米克爱你
'cause Mickey loves ya!"
谢谢你  米克  我也爱你
Thanks,Mick. I love you,too.
老天  孩子  击败他
Jesus. Go after him,kid. Go after him.
谢谢
Thanks.
你才是天使
You was the angel.
好了
There it is.
另一个袖扣呢?
What happened to his other cuff link?
我不知道  他只给了我一个
I don't know. He only give me one.
他给了别的蹩脚货
He gave it to some bum.
在这  给你  别担心这些
There you go. Don't worry about these.
好了 走吧  保罗
Let's go,Paulie.
我真不敢相信  他竟承受得了
I really can't believe it. This kid's takin' this too good. I got it.
洛奇  幸好我留在这里  对吗?  省了不少钱
Rock,it's good I kept the place,right? It saves money.
退回去
Hey,get back.
对吧? 在前门用铝装饰一下会很好看的
Right? With a little aluminum on the front,it's a winner.
谢谢你
Thank you.
洛奇 欢迎回来 我们很想念你
Welcome back,Rocky! We missed ya!
你知道这只是暂时的
This is only temporary,you know.
进来吧
Come on inside.
你好
Hello?
- 洛奇太太吗?  我是乔治·华盛顿·杜克  - 什么事?
- Mrs. Balboa? George Washington Duke. - Yes?
洛奇太太  你听得见吗? 仔细听好  你一定能听得见
Mrs. Balboa,can you hear it? Listen close. You must be able to hear it.
- 听见什么?  - 游行队伍经过的声音
- Hear what? - The parade of opportunity knocking.
你要怎样才会明白...
What will it take to get you people...
我是给你们机会卷土重来?
to realize I'm giving you a chance to pull yourselves together again?
让我作洛奇的经纪人  包你们财源滚滚来
Let me handle his career, the money will pour in,
你们就能再过人的生活
you can live like human beings.
听好  我们是过人的日子  改天你也该试试
Listen,Mr. Duke. We're living like human beings. You oughta try it.
少惹我丈夫
Leave my husband alone.
女人家
Women.
你何时开始的?
When'd you start that?
我不知道  老毛病总改不了
I don't know. It's a bad habit that comes back.
听着 我们谈的不是我  谈的是你  懂吗?
Listen. We ain't talkin' about me. We're talkin' about you,right?
- 洛奇  你好  - 你好
- Rocky,how you doin',man? - How you doin'?
- 真高兴见到你回来  - 回来的感觉真好
- Good to see you back. - Thanks. It's great to be back.
你在学校功课很好  不过在街上也要放聪明点
You're real smart in school,but you gotta be smart on the street.
什么意思?
How do you mean?
你得知道谁是老大  对方是什么来头
You gotta know who the players are and who you're talkin' to around here.
小心别被人耍诈  每个人都想设计你
Watch out for the scammers. Everybody's gonna try to scam you.
- 耍诈是什么?  - 问你爸
- What's a scam? - Ask your father.
耍诈就像是金光党
A scam is like a hustle.
- 他搞不懂  - 金光党就是...
- He don't get it. - Like a hustle's related to...
洛奇  记得我吗?  我是巴布的妈妈
Rocky! Rocky,remember me? I'm Bubba's mother.
你常拿他的头当沙袋打
You used to use his head for a punching bag.
- 玩得愉快  - 欢迎回来
- Have a nice day. - Welcome back.
- 总之金光党和骗术一样  - 他听不懂
- Anyway,a hustle's related to a con. - He don't get it.
- 欺骗  - 什么?
- A deception. - 'Scuse me?
你是说要当心受骗
You're saying beware of deceptions.
对  非常好  你很聪明  知道吗?
Yeah,that's good. Absolutely. You're very smart,you know.
原子三明治店  从前不是在这里吗?
Hey,ain't this where the Atomic Hoagie Shop used to be?
爸  我刚到这里
I'm new here,Dad.
这一带没落了
This neighborhood's comin' down with tooth decay.
- 这叫做都市凋零  - 是吗?
- It's called urban blight. - Yeah?
我告诉你  这里已经破落不堪
I'll tell you something. This place is blightin' everywhere.
修补粉刷一番就可以了 你认为如何?
Aluminum siding and some paint,this place could be okay again. You think?
你上学快迟到了  快点
Anyway,you'll be late for school. Come on.
保罗  我要和孩子私底下谈谈  男人间的对话
Paulie,I wanna talk to the kid private-like,man to smaller man.
- 你当我没感觉吗?  - 少来了  保罗
- Like I got no feelings. - Come on.
- 战争就是这样挑起的  - 放轻松  好吗?
- That's how wars start. - Relax,would you?
每个人的见解不同
So everybody's got an angle.
- 你知道吗?  - 洛奇  你运气真差
- You know? - Tough break,Rock.
每个人都有不正当的手段
Everybody's got a hustle.
这里的小孩脑筋反应快  那就是他们的生存方式
Like,see,these kids around here,they got street brains. That's how they live.
听好  他们的个性跟你以前见过的大不相同
These kids ain't like... Listen. Ain't like no personalities you grew up with.
所以你一定要保持警觉
So you gotta stay very,very sharp around here.
- 我正想这么做  - 对  这么做
- I intend to. - Yeah,intend.
- 有时候你让我觉得很笨  - 为什么?
- Sometimes you make me feel very stupid. - Why?
为什么?  因为你比我聪明 Why?
'Cause you're smarter than me and that's a fact.
- 不  我不是  - 你是的 - No,I'm not.
- Yeah,you are.
你每天学习新事物  我每天忘记新事物
It's like every day you learn something new and I forget something new.
听好  我们是一家人 Listen.
We're in this thing together.
如果你想到怎么做  不用害怕告诉我
So if you can figure out any way to fix things up,don't be afraid to tell me.
我们要团结  因为我们是什么?
We gotta stick together. 'Cause what are we?
什么?
What?
我们是什么?
What are we?
家族队
Oh! Home team.
家族队  你说对了
Home team! You know,you got that right.
我小时候也念这里  砖墙不错
I went to this school when I was a kid. Nice bricks.
午餐的牛奶很好喝
Used to get milk at lunch and everything.
当时蛮辛苦的  不过我相信你能处理的  对吧?
It was real tough then,but I think you can handle it,don't you think?
- 不行  - 你根本不知道自己在说什么!
- No way! - You don't know what you're saying!
如果你能念  我就能念  我一点也不害怕
If you went here,I can go here. I'm not scared,really.
真的?
Really?
是有一点害怕  不过这是正常的  你不觉得吗?
I guess I'm a little scared. But that's normal,don't you think?
对  我打过72场拳赛  每一场都会害怕
Oh,yeah! I had 72 fights and every one of'em,I was scared.
所以这是很正常的
So,yeah,that's real,real normal.
- 待会见  - 好的  孩子
- I'll see you later. - Okay,kid.
这是前门
Here's the front door.
没关系的  等一下  这是什么?
It's okay. Hey,wait,wait. What's this?
我的天  这是从哪里来的?
Goodness gracious! Where'd this come from?
居然把午餐的钱藏在耳朵里
It's a strange place to stash your lunch money,don't you think?
- 只是个笑话罢了  - 爸  谢谢
- It's just a lunch joke. - Thanks,Dad.
待会见
Listen,I'll see you later.
别忘了  我爱你  你是第一名  家族队
Remember,Daddy loves you. You're number one. Home team!
要守规矩  你没事的
Just be nice,right? You'll be okay.
不要管别人的女朋友  这里的人不喜欢这一套
Don't mess with nobody's girlfriend. They don't like that around here.
我真的很担心他  他没有在这里住过
I'm really worried about the kid. He ain't used to living like this.
对街上的规矩完全不熟
He don't know the streets.
我料想得到在学校会发生什么
And that school... I know what's gonna happen.
有些同学一定会找他麻烦  因为他是我儿子
Some wise guys are gonna come up 'cause he's my kid.
他们一定会整他  故意使手段对付他
They just gonna come out and give him a cheap shot.
我是说...
You know? I mean... Geez!
洛奇先生  你好  我叫汤米·甘
Mr. Balboa. How you doin'? My name's Tommy Gunn.
什么事?  你好
Yeah? How you doin'?
取这个名字一定要够狠
With a name like that,you better be tough.
确实不容易  我来自俄克拉荷马州
It ain't easy. Anyway,I come from Oklahoma.
我的业余纪录是45胜1负
I have an amateur's record of 45 to 1 .
- 18岁成为职业拳手后赛过八场  - 你是拳击手?
- I turned pro at 18,and had 8 fights.  - You're a fighter?
是的  我20岁了  想让你看看我本事
Yeah,I'm a fighter. Now that I'm 20,I'd like to show you what I got.
我存了四百元作为训练费用
I've saved up about $400,and I could pay you for a couple weeks' training.
抱歉  年轻人  我有事要谈  很高兴再次见到你
Excuse me,young man. I have business. Good to see you again,friend.
- 你好吗?  - 很好  还有什么不满足的?
- How you doing? - Fine. What more could I ask?
- 金钱和头发  - 我得去工作了
- Money and hair. - I gotta go to work.
什么?  在哪里工作?  这里吗?
What? Where? Here?
在简陋的健身室?  会影响形象的
In a sweatbox? Can't be too good for the image.
- 都市凋零  你要做什么  - 你刚才说什么？
- Urban light. What are you gonna do? - What'd you say?
- 是都市凋零   - 都市凋零
- Urban light. - It's urban blight.
请你考虑重出江湖  待遇很不错的
George would like you to put on those gloves again. It's a hell of a payday.
我已正式退休了
I'm officially expired.
你有吸引力  每场都会座无虚席
No,you have marquee value. You put butts in seats.
有头脑的生意人有钱赚就不退休
A businessman with any brain don't retire when he can still pull in bread.
只有在美国才有这种机会
Only in America do we get these kind of opportunities.
肯恩14号要争夺拳王宝座
Union Cane's goin' for the title on the 14th.
这里有几张票  请当我们的贵宾
Here's some tickets, be our guest.
我们有把握他会接受
We have a strong feeling he's gonna take it.
正是你复出的时机
That's the time to challenge him.
因为观众喜欢看你复出
Because people love comebacks!
没有比落魄拳王重拾战袍...
There's nothing in boxing more commercial than a long shot comeback...
更具票房号召力
of a down-on-his-luck,pure Snow White underdog.
正如马克·吐温所说  "品德不如金钱使人尊敬"
Like Mark Twain said,"Virtue has never been as respectable as money."
- 谁是马克吐温?  - 一个画家
- Who's Twain? - He was a painter.
你被寄予了厚望
You're the Great White Hope.
你是说白粉吧  别妄想
You mean great white dope. No,forget it.
少胡说
Hold it! Hold it. Hold the bullshit!
我知道问题所在  你认为我是三岁小孩吗?
I know what the problem is. You think I was born yesterday?
把文件拿给他看
Show him the paper.
这是你的体检报告  情况很糟  不过我们可以作弊
This is your medical report. It's not so good,but we can work around it.
- 你从哪弄来的  - 这不重要
- Where'd you get this? - It doesn't matter.
你同意出赛  乔治保证帮你弄到执照
You agree to fight Cane,George can guarantee you'll get licensed anywhere.
保证
Guaranteed!
- 你能办到?  - 没问题
- You can do this? - No problem.
现在复出至少值数百万  大好时机  千万别错过
This comeback's worth millions. The time and deal are hot! Caliente.
再赚一场也无妨
One more payday.
- 我同意  - 艾莉  你从哪里冒出来的?
- I agree. - Adrian,where'd you come from?
- 你想干嘛?  - 她出现了  好像变魔术
- What are you doing? - Mrs. Balboa appeared. She's magic.
我不认为好笑  你想说服洛奇复出吗?
I don't think you're funny. Are you trying to talk my husband into fighting?
我是在谈生意  你喜欢永远过苦日子吗?
I'm talkin' business. Do you like feelin' hard up?
你喜欢口袋空空如也的感觉吗?
Do you like reachin' in your pocket and only feelin' your leg?
我看不是吧 Do you?
I didn't think so.
我给你们最后一次摆脱失败者阴影的机会
I'm offering you your last golden opportunity to dump this loser image.
- 你以为你是谁?  - 艾莉  你不是...
- Who you talking to? - You ain't working across...
你们两个在搞什么?  这可是大好机会
Whoa! What the hell are you talking about? This is a tremendous opportunity.
谁的大好机会?  你赚大钱  洛奇残废的机会?
Opportunity for whom? For you to make money? For him to be disabled?
换个立场你会怎么做?
What would you do if the choices were reversed?
你要好好想一下
You have to think about that.
洛奇  他们根本不关心你
Rocky,they don't care about you.
你想听正经话吗?  我就说给你听
You want to get serious? Let's get serious.
你是那些希望渺茫者的梦想  他们以你为标竿
You represent the dreams of long shots and little people who identify with you.
认同是成功的关键
And identification's the key to public success.
你是真正的冠军  人们心中的冠军
You're a true champion,a true product of the people. Sell it.
趁还有人认同时赶快把握  他们不会持久的
Sell it while there are still buyers. That won't last forever.
你是拳击手  那就出赛
You're a fighter? Then fight!
想要冠军应得的待遇?  那就出赛
You want a champion's due? Then do it.
我会让你赚的钱多到可以在里面游泳
I'll make you so much money,you could swim in it.
你会游泳吧?  意下如何?
You can swim,can't you,darling? What do you say?
花点力气赚大钱
Put it there! It's time to put some hustle behind this muscle!
他退休了  不再比赛了
He's done! He's done fighting!
你真是大傻瓜
You are a damn fool!
干脆找你老婆和肯恩比赛
Maybe we oughta sign Mrs. Balboa to fight Cane,huh?
看来她才是真正有卵蛋的人
She's got the cojones in the family.
不准在我老婆面前这么说话
You don't talk like that in front of my wife.
小鬼  这不是公园板凳
That ain't no park bench,boy.
我会叫他同意的
I'll get him.
洛奇  对不起  我无意...
Rocky,I'm really sorry. I didn't wanna...
你们要私下谈吗?  我会在楼上
You guys want privacy now? I'll be upstairs.
洛奇  对不起  我...
I'm sorry. But you know...
你也知道再挨一记重拳  就可能变成残废
it just takes one bad hit and you could be an invalid.
我已经觉得自己是个残废
I feel like an invalid already!
你干嘛要回来?  你不适合这个
Why'd you come back here? You're too smart for this place.
我在家没事做  我打电话给葛洛莉
I got nothing to do. I called Gloria.
她说需要一个兼职的
She said she could use part-time help.
你为什么又回到老地方做?
Why do you wanna go back to the same place you started?
我可以这么做  你大可不必
I gotta do it,you don't gotta do it!
我是为了想跟你接近
I wanted to be there so I could be close to you.
好吧  外面有点冷
All right. It's gettin' cold out here.
我们进去吧  我了解你的苦心
Maybe we better get inside. I understand.
- 你还好吧?  - 什么?
- Are you all right? - What?
- 你还好吧?  - 我很好
- Are you all right? - Yeah,I'm all right. I'm fine.
越来越冷了  进去吧?
It's gettin' cold,okay?
艾莉  我们有离开这里吗?
Yo,Adrian. Did we ever leave this place?
我不知道
I don't know.
不介意我和你谈谈吗?
Hey,mind if I talk to you now?
我现在没心情
My head's a little busy right now.
我不知道你能否说服他  他脑袋有问题
I don't know if you'll get him. Balboa don't think straight anymore.
他们全是这样  我需要好理由
None of these bums think straight. All I need is an angle.
我现在就找洛奇比赛  我比他厉害
I'll fight Balboa right now. I'm better than Balboa ever was.
小子  你是我的人
I own the paper on you,boy.
对手  地点  战术  由我决定  明白吗?
You'll fight who,where and how I tell you. Got that?
别激怒你的老板  懂吗?
Don't aggravate the hand that feeds you. All right?
没有一个拳手脑袋是正常的
None of these bums think straight.
我需要的是诱因
All I need is a hook.
你不是洛奇的儿子吗?
Hey,ain't you Rocky's kid?
对  你是洛奇的儿子
Yeah,you're Rocky's kid.
- 你是他儿子?  - 我是  你好吗?
- You're Rocky's kid,right? - Yeah. How you doin'?
我在报上见过你
I seen your picture in the paper.
- 你知道吗?  你爸是个杂碎  - 什么?
- You know what? Your old man's a punk! - What?
这不是真的
That's not true!
你想怎么样?  你干嘛穿我的外套?
Wanna do something about it? What are you wearing my coat for?
放开他  你也想挨揍吗?
Just leave him alone. Don't take his coat.
外套给我  我不是开玩笑的
Give me my coat! I'm not kiddin'.
- 休想  - 给他
- No way! - Let him have it.
别生病了
Don't get sick now.
富家子  千万别感冒了
Hope you don't catch cold,rich boy!
左右闪避  出刺拳  就是这样
Keep it high,slip it inside. That's it. Come on.
洛奇在这里用过的杯子  十元
This cup don't interest you? Rocky drinks out of it. $10.
- 我怎么知道是真的?  - 看看唇印吧
- How I know that's the real thing? - Look at the lip marks.
我最多出五元
All right,$5. $5,no more.
成交
You got a deal.
对不起
Excuse me.
- 汤米·甘  - 在哪里换衣服?
- Tommy Gunn! - Is there someplace I can change?
里面  钱给我
In there. Gimme the money.
暂停  理查德
Time! Richard,good friend.
想打赢就得学会出刺拳
Listen to me. If you wanna survive,you gotta learn to slip the jab.
动作敏捷点  只打人  不挨打  好  休息一下
Keep it high,and hit and not get hit. Okay,take off.
- 洛奇  还记得汤米甘吧  - 记得
- Rocky,remember Tommy Gunn? - Yeah.
他说要打拳  我叫他去结婚算了
He wants to fight. I tell him to get married.
- 为什么?  - 洛奇  这是本行幽默
- Why? - That's gym humor,Rocky.
原来是那个...
Oh,okay.
小子  让我们瞧瞧你的本事
Let's see what you got,kid.
结婚  我明白
Get married. I understand.
班森  想活动一下筋骨吗?
Benson,wanna move a little?
- 好的  - 我们走吧
- All right. - Let's go.
什么是"卵蛋"?
What's a "cojones"?
卵蛋?
Cojones?
卵蛋是西班牙坚果的拉丁文
Cojones is Latin for Spanish nuts.
洛奇  我们准备好了
Rock,we're ready.
很好
Wonderful.
小子  你有带头罩吗?
Hey,kid. You got headgear?
没有  我不需要
I don't need one.
他的卵蛋不保了
He's gonna get his cojones knocked out.
好了  大伙儿准备好了?  班森  手下留情好吗
Okay. Ready,guys? Benson,go easy,all right?
- 好的  洛奇  - 开始
- Sure,okay,Rocky. - Time.
好了  别太猛  出刺拳
All right,go easy now. Slip the jab now.
小子  他叫什么名字来着?
Kid! What's his name again?
汤米·甘
Tommy Gunn.
汤米  闪躲并不算错
Tommy. Whoa. It ain't no law to duck.
左右闪躲  对了
Go side to side. That's it.
老弟  轻松点
Take it easy!
你们两个别这么拼命  这只是练拳  别太激动
Come on,you guys,lighten up. It's called sparring. Go easy.
轻一点  班森  抱住他
Hey,lighten up! Benson,tie him up.
你闻到没有?  机会的气味
Smell that? The odor of opportunity.
够了  我怎么说的?  暂停
That's it! What'd I tell ya? Hey! Time!
够了  暂停
Hey,that's it! Time!
退回去  够了
Hey,back off! That's enough.
你是怎么回事?  你疯了吗?
What's the matter with you? Are you crazy or something?
- 你是怎么搞的?  - 出来
- What's the matter with you,man? - Get outta the ring.
小子  冷静点  我很抱歉
Cool off,kid. I'm sorry about this.
他很有潜力
He stinks of opportunity.
听好  叫你放轻松  不是要你打断别人骨头
Look,goin' easy don't mean breakin' bones,kid.
我很抱歉  你认为如何?
I'm sorry,but what do you think?
我认为你根本不听我的
What do I think? You don't listen good.
你简直像在街头打架
But you fight,you brawl like you was a street fighter.
我能体会  但这是拳赛  不是打架滋事
I know somethin' about that. This is called boxing. This ain't no mugging.
对不起  但我知道我行的
I'm sorry,but I know I can do it all.
今天不适合  好吗?
Yeah? Well,not on this date. Okay?
就只有这样?
That's it?
听着  我要训练这些人
I gotta work with these kids. You guys get ready.
- 你当我经纪人好吗?  - 经纪人?
- How about you trying to manage me? - Manage?
是的  除非你认为我不够看
Yeah. Unless you think I ain't got nothin' going.
是的 不够看
Yeah,you got nothin' goin'.
你有的是本事  资质很好
You got a lot goin'. You got a lot of tools.
但我不是经纪人  我从没当过
But I ain't no manager. I ain't never been...
这儿的前任老板才是经纪人
The gentleman that owned this place,that was a manager.
我只是被人经纪的家伙
But me,I was always the managed guy.
听着  祝你好运
Look,good luck,all right?
好了  各位  开始吧
All right,guys,let's go.
快点  左右移动
Come on,move around.
对  很好
That's it,nice.
好了  快点  别乱打  灵活点
All right,come on. No cheap shots. Move it around.
你还好吧?
How you doin'?
冷吗?  你好像很冷
Cold? You look cold.
一定是天气的关系
I guess it has somethin' to do with the weather.
来  穿我的外套
Here,take my coat.
不  谢谢
No,thanks.
你男友在哪里?
Where's your boyfriend?
他?  别提了  一点礼貌都不懂
Him? Forget it. He ain't got no manners.
我叫茱儿  如果你想知道的话
I'm Jewel,if you wanna know.
我叫罗伯特
I'm Robert.
我住在这里六年了
I've been livin' here about six years.
反正不是迪士尼乐园
It ain't Disneyland.
- 你去过迪士尼乐园?  - 当然
- You been to Disneyland? - Sure.
你的口气好像大家都去过
You make it sound like everybody has.
我的外表看不出来  但是我和这里的小孩不同
I know you can't tell by the way I look,but I ain't like the other kids here.
为什么你和别人不同?
Why? What makes you so different?
大概是我想离开这里的原因吧  你也了解的
I don't know. I guess it's 'cause I wanna get out. You know how it is.
你可知道  身为意大利小孩  你的身材还算不错
You know,for an Italian kid,you ain't got a bad butt.
等我一有钱  我就要去迈阿密
First money I get,I'm goin' to Miami.
- 为何是迈阿密?  - 迈阿密需要新的牛郎
- Why Miami? - Miami needs new gigolos.
对  我看过类似报导
Yeah,I read somethin' like that.
我的背又在痛了  你怎么没有关节炎?
My back is gettin' bad. How come you don't have arthritis?
我还不够倒霉吗?
Ain't I got enough?
这地方不配艾莉  这里真令人泄气
Adrian's too good for this. This place really depresses.
保罗...
Paulie,it's...
洛奇  进来  大家都在问起你  保罗  你也来
Rock,come inside. Everybody's been asking for ya. You too,Paulie.
- 不  谢谢  我累了  - 我有点口渴
- No,thanks. I'm beat. - I'm a little thirsty.
- 保罗  你想去就去  - 巴尔博亚先生?
- You go if you want,Paulie. - Mr. Balboa?
你瞧  是汤米·甘
Look. Tommy Gunn.
你怎么还没走?  有什么要我帮忙的?
Why are you still hanging around? Is there something I can do for you?
有  我想再试试
Yeah. I'd like to try again.
我很想帮你  可是我不懂经纪
Kid,you know,I'd like to help you,but I know nothin' about no managing.
我只要你给我一个机会
I'm asking for a chance.
如果我搞砸了  我马上就走
If I screw up,you won't have to throw me out. I'll go.
- 你有什么好损失的?  - 没有  损失的是你
- What have you got to lose? - Me? Nothin'. It's what you got to lose.
- 我没什么好损失的  - 或许你有
- I got nothin' to lose. - Maybe you do.
听好  万一我不能胜任  或者你不成功
What if I don't do good and you don't make it?
我不希望你为了这个怪我
I don't want you blamin' me for this,kid.
听着  换作是我就会这么做
Here's what I would do if I was you. Listen.
如果我是你  我会先回家与家人商量
If I was you,I would go home and talk to your family.
或许会有更好的点子
Maybe you can come up with something better.
我没有家人  我只有孤单一个人
I got no family. All I got is what you see here.
你第一次出战阿波罗  我就对你瞭若指掌
I know everything about you from your first fight with Apollo Creed.
我也知道没人在乎你或给你机会
I read about how nobody cared about you,how no one gave you a chance.
我的出身与你不同  不过我像你一样有斗志
I realize I don't come from the same streets,but I'm hungry like you were.
我出道之后就一直想见你
Ever since I put on gloves,I been waitin' to meet you.
我知道只有你能让我成功
I knew that if anybody could make me a winner,it was you.
等一下  保罗  我算胜利者吗?
Hey,Paulie,you see a winner standin' here?
当然是  你是高手中的高手
Yes! Man,you beat the best!
没人敢否认这一点  洛奇  你不了解我
Nobody could ever say any different. Look,Rocky,you don't know me.
你要我做什么我都肯
But anything you want me to do,I'll do.
不行的话  我也会卖命去做
If I can't,I'll bust my butt trying.
我不是在逼你  我只是要求个机会
I'm not hustling you,man. All I'm askin' for is a chance.
一个机会罢了
Just one shot.
你饿了吗?
Are you hungry?
是的
Yeah.
真的? 走吧
Yeah? Come on.
你一定会喜欢我老婆烧的菜
You'll like the way Adrian cooks.
她煮的通心面美味无比  特别是番茄
She does amazing things with macaroni,especially tomatoes.
但我要警告你  她会放很多大蒜
But I gotta warn you,she can be a little vicious with the garlic.
那小子为何打你的脸?
So,why'd this kid smack your face?
- 没关系的  - 当然有关系  他们抢走他的外套
- It really doesn't matter. - It does matter! They took his coat.
- 我不要外套  - 有领子的那件?
- I don't want the coat. - The one with the collar?
- 我明天要去你学校一趟  - 这会把事情搞得更糟
- I'm going to your school. - It'll make things worse.
- 我不能做自认正确的事吗?  - 你认为什么是对的?
- Can't I do what I think is right? - What do you think is right?
拿球棒打他的脸
A baseball bat across the face is nice.
别教坏他好吗?  请把盘子递给我
What are you tellin' this kid? Adrian,can I have the plate?
- 抱歉  洛奇  - 我念书时也遇过这种问题
- I'm sorry. Yes,Rocky. - I had trouble when I was in school.
我每天都被一个小子追
Every day I got chased by this one kid...
直到我妈妈告诉我:"假装他是气球就好了"
till one day my mother said,"Pretend the guy's like a balloon."
气球?
Balloon?
她说狠狠揍他一顿  他就不敢了
She said,"If you pop 'em hard,these guys just go away."
我们得教孩子学习用脑处理事情
We're trying to raise our son so he can handle problems with his mind...
而不是暴力
not his muscles.
对不起
Sorry.
- 所以我才被人糟蹋  - 你不会的
- That's why I'm gonna get mangled. - You ain't gonna get mangled.
- 你教我打拳好吗?  - 拿球棒就行了
- Will you teach me how to fight? - A baseball bat would be nice.
你想一辈子靠拳头吗?
Do you wanna grow up and just use your fists?
艾莉  我认为
Adrian,I don't think it'd be so bad...
教他几招对付坏蛋  也不是什么坏事
if I taught him how to throw a few deadly punches.
汤米  你爸爸也教你打拳吗?
Tommy,did your dad teach you how to fight?
- 不尽然  我得...  - 什么?
- No,not exactly. I had to... - What?
- 别问人隐私  - 没关系
- Sweetheart,don't get personal. - That's okay.
我爸爸经常酗酒
My old man used to drink a lot,seriously.
他与酒肉朋友喝得烂醉  回家后就毒打我一顿
He'd go out with his friends tie one on,then come home and punch on me.
他也打我妈妈  他经常这么做
He'd punch on my mother,too. He did that a lot of times.
所以长大后我只想打他一顿
So growin' up,I never really thought about fighting anybody but my father.
我13岁时在学校闯了祸
When I was 13,I got in trouble at school.
他把我绑起来  狠狠抽我一顿  我一周都不能走路
He tied me down and whipped me so bad,I couldn't walk for a week.
什么事都不能做
I just couldn't do anything.
我第一个击倒的人是我爸爸
The first guy I ever knocked out was my father.
每次出场就把对手当成他
Now when I get in the ring,it's like all I see is him.
有点变态吧?
That's kinda sick,huh?
至少你还有对象可以打  不是吗?
Tommy,at least you had an old man to knock out.
- 有些人根本没有  - 有一天你也会揍你老爸
- Some of us didn't have that. - Someday you can punch out your pop.
保罗 你干嘛教坏小孩子?
Paulie,what are you tellin' the kid things like this for?
适者生存
It's the fittest of the survival.
你今晚住哪里?
Tommy,where you stayin' tonight?
- 有地方睡吗?  - 我会找到地方睡的
- You got a place? - I'll find someplace to stay.
这样好了  地下室还有个房间
I tell you,we got room in the basement. It's nice.
- 那我呢?  - 那是你儿子的房间
- What about me? - Your son is sleeping down there.
- 他可以和叔叔一起睡  - 我算什么  救济站吗?
- He could stay with his uncle. - What am I,a pit stop?
我不想造成各位不便  我找别的地方睡
I don't wanna cause any problems. I can find someplace to stay.
没关系  反正只是暂时的  对吧?
It's okay. It's just for a little while. Right?
不要客气
No problem at all. It'll be all right.
孩子  我很感激你  外面很冷
Kid,I appreciate it. Is that all right? It's cold outside.
- 我可不换床单  - 你何时换过了?
- I'm not changing no sheets. - Since when have you ever?
汤米  你来看一下房间吧
Tommy,come on down and we'll show you the place.
下去让你爸看看你今天的成果  快去
Why don't you go downstairs,show your father what you did today? Come on.
孩子  你不会尿床吧?
Junior,your plumbin' don't leak,do it?
- 你认识他?  - 认识 他出拳很猛
- You know this guy? - Yeah. He hits hard.
- 艾莉的菜烧得真好  - 对  很好吃
- Adrian,she can really cook. - She's okay.
听着  我们没时间整理地下室
Listen,Tommy. We ain't had a chance to get this place too nice...
等下大伙儿一起收拾一下
so we'll get it together in a little while.
这才是拳击手的目标
Wow,man. This is what it's all about!
- 我的天  - 为何全放在地下室?
- Holy mackerel! - Why do you keep this stuff down here?
你何时整理的?  你把所有东西都排好了  太美了
When'd you do this? You fixed it like this. It's beautiful!
你还上了油漆  你何时整理的?
You painted! When'd you get a chance to do this,kid?
放学后  这没什么
After school. It's no big deal.
- 拳套是哪里来的?  - 这个吗?
- Where'd you get the glove? - This?
谢谢  这是我最心爱的东西
Thanks. This is one of my favorite objects.
米克在他过世之前送给我的
Mickey give me this before he departed.
- 它是洛奇·马西安诺的袖扣  - 真的?
- It was Rocky Marciano's cuff link. - Really?
- 真的?  洛奇·马西安诺?  - 是的
- The real Rocky Marciano? - Yeah.
你令我又想起米克  我有样东西给你看
You got me thinkin' about Mickey. I wanna show you somethin'. Come on.
他很久以前告诉我的  他说...
He told me a long time ago,he says...
拳击是九成的智慧  再加上一成的力量
that fightin' is 90% in the skull and 10% in the body.
他是这么说
He said this.
爸  我今天认识一个很棒的女孩
I met this really nice girl today. She's great.
- 真的?  太好了  - 她比莎菈漂亮多了
- Yeah? That's wonderful. - She's a lot better than Sarah.
孩子  别换话题  待会再和你聊
Don't change the station. I'll be right back with you.
我先和汤米聊聊
I just wanna tell Tommy a few things.
你在奥兰多最好的朋友是谁?
Who was your best friend in Orlando?
是俄克拉荷马州
Uh,that's Oklahoma.
- 对  没错  - 艾瑞克·爱德
- Oh,yeah. - Eric Elder.
不  不对  你最好的朋友是法兰克·恐惧
No,no,no. Your best friend is a guy named Frankie Fear.
恐惧是拳手最好的朋友
You see,fear is a fighter's best friend.
用不着不好意思
It ain't nothin' to be ashamed of.
恐惧令你保持警觉  令你清醒  令你有生存的意志
Fear keeps you sharp,keeps you awake,makes you wanna survive.
但重点是你得学习控制它
Know what I mean? But you gotta learn how to control it.
因为恐惧就像一把火  在内心深处燃烧
'Cause fear is like this fire. And it's burnin' deep inside.
只要详加控制  就能使你振奋
If you control it,Tommy,it's gonna make you hot.
如果让它控制了你
But you see,if this thing here controls you...
你的一切就会化为灰烬 没错
it's gonna burn you and everything else around you up,that's right.
总之  这些是恩师教给我的
Anyway,these are the things that was taught to me...
你愿意的话  我就传授给你
and if you want,I'd like to teach to you.
这表示你要当我的经纪人?
So this mean you're gonna manage me?
- 当然  家族队  - 好吧
- Absolutely! Hey,home team! - All right!
加油
Let's go for it.
要不要先示范几招?
Mind showing me a few things?
当然  我要教的事太多了
Sure. I'm gonna show you a lot of things.
富家子  你今天带了多少钱?
Hey,rich boy,how much you got in your pocket today?
- 没有钱  - 快拿出来
- Nothin'. - Let's have it.
- 没有  我身上没钱  - 快拿出来给我
- I got nothin'! - Come on,give me the money.
- 快点  - 我要买午餐的
- Come on! - I gotta eat!
他饿了  要吃东西  吃拳头吧
He's hungry! He's gotta eat. Well,eat this.
我拿到了  快走
I got it. Go!
卡敏神父
Father Carmine!
Yo! Father Carmine!
- 也许他不在家  - 神父一向都在家
- Maybe he's not home. - Priests is always home.
洛奇
Rocky!
神父  我不想太打扰你
I didn't wanna disturb you that much,Father.
非常好  一切都很好
Excellent. Everything is perfect.
神父  这是我的新朋友汤米·甘
Father,this is my new friend,Tommy Gunn.
汤米是拳手  我准备当他经纪人
I was wondering,Tommy is a fighter and I'm supposed to be his manager.
如果你不忙的话  帮我一个忙
So I was wondering if you could do me a favor if you ain't busy.
请你替我们赐福
If you could throw us down a couple of blessings...
第一  我会是个称职的经纪人
like that I don't mess up being the manager...
第二  他能像我所想的那么棒  不会受伤
and that Tommy does as good as I think he can do,great,and don't get hurt.
可以吗
Can you do that?
我就喜欢他这么做  神父  谢谢你  感激不尽
I love when he does that. Thanks,Father. I appreciate this.
不客气
Anytime.
教堂见
I'll see you in church.
你干嘛这么做?
What'd you do this for?
有神明保佑总是好事
It don't hurt havin' an angel in your corner.
走吧
Come on.
- 洛奇  近来可好?  - 好的很
- Hey,Rock,how's it goin'? - Doin' great!
慢一点  免得开罚单
Slow down,we'll give you a ticket.
- 他是汤米甘  未来的拳王  - 你好吗?  汤米
- This is Tommy Gunn. He'll be champion. - How you doin',Tom?
散开  别打了
Break it up. Break it up.
别靠近绳子
Get off the ropes!
- 放轻松点  懂吗?  - 我得多练习
- Go easy,all right? - I need more work.
- 不必 你已经准备好了  - 我得多练习  他太厉害了
- No,you're ready. - This guy's killing me.
你很完美  明白吗?
You're perfect. You understand?
- 我没胜算  - 闭嘴
- I feel weak. - Shut up!
英雄与懦夫间的唯一的差别
The only difference between the hero and a coward...
就是英雄勇往直前不畏生死
is the hero's willing to go for it,willing to take the shot.
这小子也一样害怕  你们都害怕
This guy's scared,too. You're both scared.
记得我们曾谈论过畏惧 还有燃烧内心的火?
Remember we were talking about fear and how it was like this fire?
你要学习控制  因为不是烧死你就是烧死他
You gotta control it 'cause it'll burn you up or burn him up.
你要善加利用  我不会做伤害你的事
You gotta make it work for you. I would never do nothin' to hurt you.
明白我说什么吗?  畏惧就像这团火
Understand what I'm sayin'. Fear is like this fire.
让它燃烧直到火山爆发
Let it burn until it becomes like this volcano.
时机成熟时  看准空隙  全部爆发在他身上
And when the time is right,explode all over this guy!
你能制伏他  全靠你的心智
You can take him. It's all heart.
不在于硬拼  心智与火
It ain't all muscle. It's all heart and fire!
去击败他
Now you do it.
记住  我就像你肩上的天使保佑你
Remember,I'm like this angel sitting on your shoulder.
我不会让你出事的 懂吗?  上吧
I ain't gonna let nothin' happen to you. Go.
加油  汤米  出刺拳
Come on,jab!
左拳  右拳
Explode! Left,right!
打身体
The body!
太好了
All right!
打身体  汤米
Go to the body!
对  就是这样
That's it.
你还好吧?
Man,you okay?
汤米·甘  威力像把枪  对不对?
Tommy Gunn,you got some guns!
加把劲  35下
Drive through it. Thirty-five.
十下  你办得到的  对了
Ten. Come on,you can do it. That's it.
加油  撑起来  太好了
Got it! Bring it up! Yes!
我赢了  这次我赢了
I gotcha! I gotcha this time!
汤米  这些拳击短裤意义重大
Tommy,these trunks is very special to me.
小子  打得好
Kid,that was great! Great work!
不错
All right,kid.
我赢了  真不敢相信
I beat the man! I don't believe it.
你确实做到了  汤米  你身手敏捷
You sure did. You're very swift.
梅林  听好  我有主意了
Merlin,listen. Got an idea.
我终于有办法逼洛奇出赛
I think we can finally nail Balboa.
他们又在等你了
They're waitin' again.
如果你钱不够  我身上有一元
If you don't got enough money,I've got almost a dollar.
- 留着吧  - 又在躲我?
- Save it. - Slumming again,bimbo?
- 背包里有什么?  - 闭嘴
- What you got in the bag? - Shut up.
你再走我就打得你满地找牙
Take two more steps,I'm gonna pound your teeth out.
试试看
Go for it!
他说什么?  这小子脑子有毛病
What'd he say? Punk's losin' his mind.
- 你说什么?  - 试试看
- What'd you say? - Go for it!
快点  过来跟我打
Come on! Put up your hands!
不要  反正我也不喜欢他
No way! I didn't like him anyway.
外套是我的吧
Think that belongs to me.
你愿意的话  现在就一笔勾销
If you want to end it,let's end it now.
我没意见
I got no problem with that.
回头见
See you later.
- 我真不敢相信  - 你会告诉你爸爸吗? 走
- I can't believe it. - You gonna tell your dad? Let's go!
好  就是这样  再来一次
Good,that's it. One more time.
你出拳很猛  不过得多练习闪躲
Tommy,you're doing great with the combinations.
但是你得学会像汽车挡风玻璃上的刮水器一样移动
But you gotta learn to move side to side like a windshield wiper...
脸上才不会吃拳头
so you ain't gettin' kicked in the face with the jab.
爸  我把外套要回来了 你看  我的外套
Dad! I got my coat back! Look,I got my coat!
孩子  太棒了  了不起
That's great! That's beautiful!
我击败那小子  同学为之疯狂
I trashed this guy! Everybody in the school went crazy!
- 洛奇  我的拳击感快没了  - 听着  我要和汤米练拳了
- Rocky,I'm coolin' down. - I gotta get back with Tommy.
我们要努力  他正在平静下来
We gotta work out. He's coolin' down.
告诉你妈  她一定喜欢听的  棒极了
Go tell your mom. She likes to hear things like that. That's beautiful!
汤米  我们开始吧
Okay. Let's go,Tommy.
打得好
Lookin' good.
快看汤米的厉害
Whoa! Look at Tommy go.
肯恩  新科重量级拳王
Union Cane,the new heavyweight championof the world!
- 你想我有机会吗?  - 当然
- Think I have a chance at that? - Absolutely.
汤米 只要有一双拳头 加上一颗好心脏 人人都有机会
Anybody that's got two fists and a good heartbeat,you got a chance.
你输了
You're out!
强硬起来
Come on! Get tough!
你的黄金手
Boy,you've got hands of gold!
过来一下  我介绍个人给你认识
I want to introduce you to somebody. Karen,come here.
比赛结束
That's it! It's over!
汤米  击倒他
Back him up.
比赛结束
That's it!
- 那是你的船  - 什么船?
- There's your boat. - What boat?
快沉没的那艘船
The one that's sinking.
第一把交椅的汤米·甘
Tommy Gunn at the top.
只要你为杜克打拳...
You come with the Duke...
包你荣华富贵  洛奇只能干瞪眼
you can get the kind of payday fighters for Balboa can only dream about.
胜利者享有一切战利品
To the victor goes the spoils.
汤米  出刺拳
Lift the jab!
你输了
You're out!
你赢了 成功了
You did it,man!
- 我现在可以争拳王了吧?  - 很快就可以了
- Now will I get a shot at the title? - You're gonna get one real soon.
宝贝  你还好吗?
Baby,how are you?
汤米只花二分十秒赢得胜利
The winner at two minutes,ten seconds...
- 汤米何时挑战肯恩?  - 这件事得从长计议
- When's Tommy goin' up against Cane? - We gotta talk about that.
去访问别人  好吗?  洛奇  他不值得的
Get back. He ain't worth it,buddy.
他打得很好
He fought a great fight.
你的船沉了  洛奇  没希望了
The ship is sunk,Rocky. It's sunk.
他可能塞车了  否则早该到了
Probably got hung up in traffic. He should've been here by now.
为什么?
Why?
现在是圣诞节  他应该陪家人一起过
It's Christmas. He should be with his family.
或许他不认为我们是他的家人
Maybe he doesn't think this is his family.
当然是  艾莉  你看
Sure it is. Look at this.
我要送他这个  你认为如何?
I want to give this to him. What do you think?
你给他的已经够多了
I think you've given enough.
得了  艾莉  他也给了我们不少
Come on,Adrian. He's given us things too.
他让我们东山再起  不是吗?  别这样  今天是圣诞节
He's given us like a second shot,right? Come on. It's Christmas.
没错  只有在美国
Right. Only in America.
才能得到最好的享受  想保有这一切就得永远领先
Having the best,wearing the best. To keep it up,you got to stay on top.
- 没有人会记得亚军的  - 我就不会
- Nobody remembers number two,kid. - I sure don't.
我查过拳击协会的资料
I checked with the Boxing Commission.
你和洛奇没有正式的合约关系
Seems there's no formal contract between you and Balboa.
没有  只是君子协定
Nothin'.Just a handshake.
拳击这一行很复杂  你得时时保持警觉
This is a complex business,and you've got to stay sharp!
用不着我多说  对不对?
I don't have to tell you that,do I?
长期活在洛奇的阴影下 一定很不好受
It's gotta be damn difficult living in Rocky's shadow,being called his puppet.
没有人能像你忍受这么久
Nobody could've done it as long as you have.
我很担心
I'm afraid.
如果你再这样下去
I'm afraid that if you keep going the way you're going...
你就会错过大好机会
you're gonna be watching the parade go by.
一点不错
Exactly.
你还没享受真正的光荣  你也不会
You haven't had the big payday yet,and won't until you fight top contenders.
除非你挑战真正的一流拳手
And those top contenders I do surely own.
我有一份合约
I got the contracts.
这是个复杂的行业
It's a complex business.
如果你想得到最好的就要跟对人
But if you want the best,then go with the best.
洛奇呢?
What about Rocky?
洛奇还是可以训练你  他表现得很棒
Rocky can still train you. He's done a wonderful job.
这里是二万元
Here's $20,000.
就当作是定金
Take it as an advance.
也该好好享受一番了
Time to put some hustle behind this muscle.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas!
Merry Christmas.
大消息  你们一定不相信谁在屋顶上
Stop the press! You can't believe who just come up on the roof.
他才刚刚抵达  你们猜他是谁?
He just landed there and crashed. Who do you think it is?
是不是驯鹿?
Do I hear reindeer on my roof?
驯鹿角  真难以置信  有一大群
You know,antlers! It's unbelievable! Like a billion...
快来  看看谁来了
Whoa! Look who's here.
你们都认识他
You know this guy.
- 你家人真怪异  - 难道我不知道?
- You've got a weird family. - Don't I know.
等他再下来就是明年圣诞节了
It's gonna be next Christmas before he gets down.
大家为圣诞老公公鼓掌
Let's put it together for Santa!
圣诞快乐! 哟...
Merry Christmas. Yo,yo,yo.
圣诞老公公  你说错了 应该是哈...
I don't think you got it right,Santa. It's,"Ho,ho,ho."
有什么不同? 我家乡都是哟...
What's the freakin' difference? Where I come from it's yo,yo,yo.
看来圣诞老公公喝醉了
Looks like we've got a 90-proof Santa.
圣诞老公公
Santa...
告诉孩子们你从北极带来什么礼物
tell the kids what you've got in the bag you brought from the North.
- 我带了一包要洗的衣服  - 你拿错包包了
- I've got my laundry. - You got the wrong bag.
- 胖子  别挡路  - 小心点
- Come on,chubby,get out of the way. - Watch it.
让圣诞老公公坐一下  过来  小子  你乖不乖?
Let Santa take a seat. Little boy,you been nice?
- 来  坐下  - 你何不告诉圣诞老公公要什么?
- Come here. Sit down. - Tell Santa what you need.
他拉我衣服  我什么都不需要
You're stretching the clothes! I don't need nothin'!
告诉他你真正想要什么
Tell Santa what you really want.
他不是圣诞老公公  是保罗叔  别骗人了
That ain't Santa! It's Uncle Paulie. Get real.
别骗人了是什么意思?  你干嘛这样说话?
"Get real"? Why you talkin' like that?
我们只是想快乐一下  圣诞老公公也在这里
We're trying to have a good time. Santa's here and everything.
太蠢了
It's stupid!
一点也不蠢  大家只是假装一下
It ain't stupid. We're just trying to pretend here.
本来就是该假装一下  好像玩游戏一样  你懂吗?
You're supposed to be pretending. It's like this game,right?
我不喜欢假装 你们去和圣诞老公公说话算了
I don't like pretending. You guys talk to Santa.
我不是和他们谈  我是要和你谈
I ain't talkin' to them,I'm talkin' with you.
与家人和乐融融是很重要的
See,it's very important that you spend time with the family...
要让这个精神代代相传
and have a good time and get the spirit goin'.
这是好事  明白吗?
It's good,right?
有什么好的?  我们走吧
Good for what? Let's go.
他朋友在场
His friends are here.
- 他是无心的  - 我知道他想要什么
- He doesn't want to. - I know what he wants.
- 你哪会知道我想要什么?  - 因为我了解你
- How do you know what I want? - 'Cause I know you.
你了解我?
You know me?
他自以为了解我
He thinks he knows me.
我才不要过圣诞节  好吗?
I ain't celebratin' nothing,okay?
你怎么了?
Come here. What's the matter with you?
我们以前都是这样过  一直都很快乐  艾莉
We always done this before,we had a good time.
我们不必改变什么
We don't have to change nothin'.
还记得去年我们玩得多快乐?
Do you remember last year when we had fun,we had a good time?
这不是去年  你也不一样了
It ain't last year,and you ain't the same,either.
什么
What?
艾莉  我做错什么了?
Adrian,what'd I do?
去和他谈谈
Go talk to him.
我早料到会发生此事
Even I could've saw this thing happening.
我当初早该去迈阿密
I should've went to Miami when I had the chance.
你想谈?
You wanna talk?
那就谈吧
Let's talk.
我以为我们父子情深
I thought we were supposed to be like very close.
- 我爱你  - 不 你不爱
- I love you. - No,you don't.
我当然爱你  你还记得吗 Sure
I do. Remember what the deal was?
我们应该像手指一样紧紧在一起
We was supposed to be tight,like crossed fingers.
你只想和汤米紧紧在一起  这才是你真正的意思
No. You want you and Tommy to be tight. That's what you're takin' about.
- 别这么说  - 为什么不行?
- Don't say that. - Why can't I say it?
你总是汤米长  汤米短的
Since he's been here,it's "Tommy this,Tommy that."
你不给我时间  我也没时间陪你
You don't have no time for nobody,so I got no time for you.
你说什么?  你好像另外一个人
What are you saying? You're like another person.
你才是另外一个人
You're the other person!
你说我是你心目中第一人  你骗人
You said I would be number one to you. You lied!
你骗了我  也骗了妈妈
You lied to me and to Mom.
我从没骗你  汤米需要我帮忙
I never lied to you. Tommy needed my help.
我也是
So did I.
记得你告诉我  要小心被人欺骗吗?
Remember when you said to watch out for scams and deceptions?
是的
Yeah.
你才是该小心的
You're the one that should've watched out.
- 你要去哪里?  - 出去走走
- Where you going? - Out.
- 什么时候回来?  - 晚一点
- When you coming back? - Later.
到底几点?
When?
洛奇太太  佳节愉快
Season's greetings,Mrs. Balboa!
你去打发他们
Take care of these people.
快看  有位圣诞老公公
Behold! A Santa for all seasons!
你们迷路了吗
You guys lost?
正好相反  我是专程拜访
Au contraire,mon ami. I know exactly where I am.
洛奇  猜猜看是谁来晚餐了?
Rocky,guess what's comin' to dinner!
汤米·甘交了新朋友
Tommy Gunn's got new friends!
新的一年  新的朋友
New friends for a new year!
这算什么? 保罗
Paulie, please?
好美的圣诞树  真漂亮
Nice tree. Charming.
汤米  你好
Tommy,how you doin'?
圣诞快乐  阁下
Merry Christmas,milord! Greetings!
- 你好吗?  - 听着
- How you doin'? - Listen.
我不想打扰太长时间  只是来祝你圣诞快乐
I don't want to take up time. I just wanted to give a season's greetings.
- 我不需要礼物  - 那就送给邻居
- I don't need no presents. - Give 'em to the neighbors.
你把他训练得很棒  这是不争的事实
You've done a hell of a job with the man. Facts are facts.
如果看不出他有冠军相  那我不就成了瞎子
I'd have to be blind if I didn't say a title shot isn't in the cards.
- 冠军相?  - 我们合作是天衣无缝
- Title shot? - We'll work beautifully together.
没问题
No problems.
没有摩擦  只有和谐
No friction. Only harmony.
该是让他好好表现的时候了
It's time to put some hustle behind this muscle.
汤米有些事要和你讨论
Tommy boy here has got a little something personal to discuss with you.
我先告辞了  圣诞快乐
So I'm gonna be sayin' good night. Merry Christmas.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas.
- 回头见  - 再见
- See you soon. - Bye.
抱歉我来晚了  晚餐耽误了
I'm sorry I'm late. I ended up having dinner.
没关系  汤米
It's okay,Tommy.
艾莉烧了些好菜  大概凉了
Adrian cooked something,but it's probably all cold now.
不如再做些三明治
We can always make sandwiches.
我不想做三明治  你干嘛带他来这里
I don't want to make sandwiches. Tommy,why did you bring him here?
他只是想问候一声  不介意我们到外面聊一下
He wanted to come by. Rocky,could I talk to you outside about some things?
当然好
Yeah,sure.
很晚了  我们十点以前要赶到
It's getting late. We have to be there by 10:00.
- 洛奇?  - 不  没关系
- Rocky? - I know. It's okay.
你要跟我谈什么
Tommy,what'd you want to talk to me about?
- 车程不是很远吗?  - 是的
- Isn't it a long drive? - Yeah.
你觉得怎么样?
So,what do you think?
- 你从哪弄来的?  - 杜克送我的
- Where'd you get this? - Duke gave it to me.
或许你该把车子还给他
Maybe you ought to give this thing back,you know?
我就知道你会这么说
I knew it! I knew you would say that!
还给他?  为什么?  他欣赏我的拳击
Give it back? Why? The guy likes the way I fight.
- 快十点了  - 好  我们赶得上的
- It's almost 10:00. - We'll make it.
汤米  你还不明白他的用意吗
I know,but you see what he's doing?
别中了他的离间之计  我们才是好搭档
Don't let him put nothin' between us.
他只是要栽培我争夺拳王
Put what? The guy was talkin' about gettin' a shot.
我们不需要他
But we don't need him.
你会有机会的  到时候这玩意儿买十部都行
You're gonna get a shot. You'll be able to buy ten of these things.
你何时才会清醒?  我们眼睁睁错失良机
When are you gonna wake up? We're watchin' the parade go by.
- 什么机会?  - 天大的好机会 - Look.
What are you talkin' about? - The big time.
照现在这样子  我会很久都没有机会
The way I'm goin',I won't get a shot at the title for a long time.
我的纪录这么好  22场全胜
I've got a perfect record. I'm 22 and 0.
钱在哪里
Where's the money? Where?
我们什么大钱都没赚到  没有他也别想办到
We haven't made serious money yet,and we won't without the man.
我指的不是钱  钱自然会赚到
I ain't talkin' about the money. The money is gonna be there.
我指的是你的名声  不要签卖身契  我们不需要他
I'm talking about your rep,Tommy. Don't sell out. We don't need this guy.
杜克是个好人  把车顶拉上
Listen. Duke is a wonderful man. Put the top up.
别管车顶的事  我明天和他签约
Forget about the top! I'm signing papers with the man tomorrow.
你签下合约就是他的财产了
You sign them papers,you're like his property.
你会失去自由  这是卑鄙的交易
You got no control. This is a dirty business.
全是些土匪流氓
It's full of these thieves and gangsters.
他们假装承诺一大堆好处  骗取年轻拳手的信任
They promise the world to every good young fighter who comes along.
然后再榨干他们
They suck 'em dry.
等没有利用价值时就甩掉他们
They leave 'em in the gutter broke when they ain't worth nothin'.
这一行就是这么回事  杜克这种人
That's the way this business is run. Guys like Duke...
知道他是什么吗?  他是个吸血鬼  靠你的血汗满足自己
You know what he is? He's a vampire. He's living off your blood.
我对你的方式正是米克对我的
The thing I'm trying to do is what Mick done to me.
他让我尽量远离卑鄙的交易  正是我要为你做的
He tried to keep me away from the dirty part of the business,like I'm doing.
我不是你  你也不是米克  你何时才会明白?
I ain't you,and you ain't Mick! When you gonna understand that?
这是做生意  你需要
When you gonna understand this is a business? And you need...
- 什么? 头脑吗?   - 是你说的  不是我
- Brains? - You said that,not me.
你是说我没脑子吗
You sayin' I got no brains?
你带我进拳坛  但杜克给我争拳王的机会
You took me as far as you could,but Duke gave me a title shot,you didn't.
如果想继续训练我  可以  不想的话就算了
If you want to keep training me,do it. If you don't,don't!
但要照我的方式  不然就拉倒
But it's my way or the highway!
穿上外套
Put on your coat.
这么做不值得
Come on. It's not worth it.
值得  他只是迷失方向
It is worth it. He's just confused.
- 你没认清现实  - 我看得很清楚
- You don't see what's happening. - I do see!
他被杜克耍得团团转
He's twisted around by Duke.
不  是你  不是他 你不能越活越回去
It's you,it's not him. You can't live backwards.
你无法令时光倒流  我们是活在此时此地
You can't turn back the clock. We live now,we live here.
我当然知道  你以为我是笨蛋?
I know where we live! You think I'm stupid?
我不像你想像中那么笨
I'm not as dumb as you think I am.
你以为我不明白吗?  我知道我们的处境
You don't think I can smell it? I see where we are!
我不要过这种日子  我要家人过好日子
I don't want this no more. I want something different for the family.
我不要这些
I don't want this!
我回来这里可不是让别人耻笑的
Did I come back here and get my brains beat out for these guys to say...
洛奇只是一个蹩脚货而已
"There goes Balboa.Just another bum in the neighborhood"?
- 我不要这样  - 不  别这样  没人这么说
- I didn't want this. - No,nobody said that.
是我说的  艾莉
I'm sayin' this,Adrian.
每当那小子出场比赛  我就感觉赢了
When that kid was in the ring,I was winning.
- 他赢就等于我赢了  - 你赢?
- When he was winning,I was winning. - You were winning?
这是我赢得尊敬的最后机会
It was like my last chance to get some respect for us.
- 好了  我尊敬你  - 你不能尊敬我
- I respect you! - You can't respect me!
- 不  你做不到  - 我可以
- No,you can't! - I do!
你比赛时所受的伤
All those beatings you took in the ring...
我是感同身受  我知道你的感觉
I took them with you.
我知道像汤米这种人一出现  你又恢复生气
I know how you feel. When somebody like Tommy comes along,you feel alive.
但他不是你  他没有你的意志
But he's not you. He doesn't have your heart.
所有你击败的对手  你是用意志击败他们  不是蛮力
All those fighters you beat,you beat 'em with heart,not muscle.
米克知道这点  你和米克才显得特别
That's what Mickey knew. That's why you and Mickey were special.
可是米克已经死了
But Mickey's dead.
如果你想传承  应该传给你儿子
If there's something you want to pass on,pass it on to your son.
看在老天分上  你儿子已经迷失  他需要你
For God's sake! Your son is lost! He needs you!
我知道汤米令你感觉很棒
I know Tommy makes you feel great.
他让你觉得又要赢得胜利
He makes you feel like you're winning again.
但是你却输掉家人
But you're losing us!
洛奇  你要失去家人了
You're losing your family!
对不起
I'm sorry.
只有你了解我
It was always you and me.
艾莉  对不起
I'm sorry,Adrian.
我不知道你们怎样
I don't know about you guys...
我可要离开这
but I gotta get out of here.
- 我们去海边  好吗?  - 好  我们走
- What do you say we go to the shore? - Let's go.
太好了  我们要怎么去?
Great. How we gonna get there?
怎么去?  伸大拇指搭便车
What do you mean? We throw our thumbs in the air. We'll hitchhike.
他想干嘛?
Ah,what's he want?
- 要我陪你吗?  - 不用
- You want me to stay with you? - No.
我老爸已经够烦了  走吧
I've got enough problems with my old man. Come on.
- 你不会打他吧?  - 不  我不会打他
- You ain't gonna hit him,are you? - No,I ain't gonna hit him.
孩子  你何时开始学抽烟?
Yo,kid,when you start smokin'?
我不知道  你没抽过烟吗?
I don't know. Didn't you ever smoke?
有  你可知我做过不少坏事?
Yeah. I done a lot of bad things,you know?
那又怎样?
So?
我后来学乖了
So,I wised up.
好的  也许有一天我也会学乖
So maybe I'll wise up someday,too.
也许今晚是我们俩学乖的好机会
Maybe tonight's a good night for both of us to start wising up.
你放心
Don't worry about it.
我当然会担心 我们应该是很亲近的
I gotta worry about it. The deal was we were supposed to be tight,right?
汤米呢?  你不是跟他很亲近?
What about Tommy? You're tight with him,too.
对...
Yeah,well.
那是过去的事了
That was yesterday,you know?
知道吗?  孩子
You know,kid...
记得你跟我说欺骗的事
remember you were telling me a long time ago about deceptions...
我跟你说小心耍诈吗?
and I was tellin' you about scams?
我应该听你的才对  我却反而对你说教
I should've listened to you. I was trying to teach you.
但是你却教了我
All right? But you were teaching me.
而我却不听  我当时不知道我犯了错误
And I didn't wise up. I didn't know and I made mistakes.
我做了...
And I do things...
那使我耿耿于怀  我会忘记很多事
It bothers me that I forget a lot of things.
我知道自己做错了
I know I made a few mistakes.
但我希望能再跟你一起 But
I would love to hang out with you again.
只有你和我
Just you and me.
我发誓
I swear to God...
这次只有你和我
it's just gonna be you and me this time.
家族队?
Home team?
对  家族队
Yeah. Home team.
- 孩子  你想听个笑话吗?  - 当然  说来听听
- Kid,you wanna hear a joke? - Sure. Why not?
- 敲敲门  - 哪位?
- Knock,knock. - Who's there?
- 鲔鱼  - 鲔鱼什么?
- Tuna fish. - Tuna fish who?
钢琴可以调音  鱼不能调
You can tune a piano,but you cannot tune a fish.
你有进步了
You're gettin' better.
对  这个笑话不错
Yeah,that's a good one.
把门关上  小孩藏好  决战时刻来临了
Lock the door and hide the kids. It's time to wage war!
汤米·甘是洛奇的得意门生
Tommy Gunn is said to be such a student of Rocky Balboa's style...
报界为他取绰号为复制突击队
he's been nicknamed by the press "The Clone Ranger."
轻松点  洛奇  他不值得你紧张
Relax. He ain't worth the stress.
保罗  不是他的关系
It ain't him,Paulie.
力量有如涡轮增压机
Turbo charged!
汤米·"机关枪"
Tommy "The Machine" Gunn!
看来观众对于汤米...
Looks like the fans are unhappy with Tommy Gunn...
对洛奇忘恩负义之举有些不满
for leaving Rocky Balboa behind.
当然了  这小子人见人厌
Of course. He's nobody's sweetheart,that kid.
体重是令人印象深刻的242磅
At 242 very impressive pounds...
现任世界重量级拳王
the present world heavyweight champion...
尤尼·肯恩
Union Cane!
保罗  他的状况似乎很棒?
Looks like he's in great shape,don't it?
裁判将选手叫至场中
The referee calling both fighters...
你看汤米  他有点紧张
Whoa,Tommy's lookin' a little tight. He's nervous,you know?
他很紧张  就像我和阿波罗比赛的感觉一样
Like the way I felt when I was fightin' with Apollo.
洛奇  那小子不是你 他永远比不上你
He ain't you. Hardly ever was,that kid.
别这样  给他个机会
Give him a break,would you?
汤米  照我教你的打
Do what you was told.
前后跳跃  左右闪躲  避开他的刺拳
In and out,side to side. Don't eat the jab.
快离开绳子  你瞎了吗?
Off the ropes! You blind?
他这样会被修理的很惨
He's gettin' hit with everything but the ring posts.
快  肯恩  修理他  加油
Let's rumble. Go for it,Cane.
小子  你是怎么搞的?  就是这样
Come on,Tommy. What's the matter with you? That's it!
出刺拳  移动  左右闪躲
Slip the jab. Move side to side.
像节拍器一样来回移动
Back and forth like a metronome. Side to side.
对了
That's it!
你看  他全部都记得
You see,he remembers everything.
汤米  加油  我就在你身旁  照我的打法
Come on. I'm in there. Do what I'm doin'.
照我的打法  来回移动  左右闪
Do what I'm doin'. Side to side!
不要让他还手
Don't let him up!
重击...
Roll! Roll! Roll!
摆平他
Dig! Dig!
重量级拳王肯恩被击倒了
The heavyweight champion Cane is down!
一  二  三
One! Two! Three!
四  五
Four! Five!
六  七
Six! Seven!
八  九
Eight Nine!
十  你输了
Ten! You're out!
各位女士先生  以击倒取胜
Ladies and gentlemen,by way of a knockout...
新拳王产生了
we have a new champion...
汤米·"机关枪"
Tommy "The Machine" Gunn!
恭喜  你赢得嘘声如雷的胜利
Congratulations. A sensational upset victory!
身为新任拳王有何感想?
You're now the champion of the world. How do you feel?
我太高兴了  我不知道这些人是怎么搞的
Never better. I don't know what's wrong with these people...
因为你不是冠军  只是个杂碎
Because you're not a champion. You're a crumb-bum dirtbag.
饶了他吧  他表现得很棒
Give him a break. He's doin' something wonderful.
- 拳王万岁  - 我要感谢
- Long live the king! - I'd like to thank the man...
促成这一切的人
who made this happen.
我要感谢他让我相信这一切
I'd like to thank the man who made me believe all this could happen.
他就像我肩上的天使  乔治·华盛顿·杜克先生
The man who's been like an angel on my shoulder,Mr. George Washington Duke!
世界新任拳王终于诞生了 汤米·"机关枪"
There you have it,a new world champion,Tommy "The Machine" Gunn.
告诉各位  至少令我意外的是...
It's a big surprise,at least to me,that the new champion...
他竟然感谢杜克而非提拔他的人
thanked Duke instead of the guy that got him here.
现场观众并不高兴
This crowd is unhappy. The only person...
洛奇...
Rocky! Rocky!
- 看太多电视对眼睛有害  - 我的眼睛没事
- Too much TV is bad for the eyes. - My eyes are okay.
看太多电视对耳朵不好
Too much TV is bad for my ears.
- 小鬼  比赛很精彩吧?  - 爸  还好
- Hi,slugger. Good fight,huh? - It's okay.
你才是真正的冠军  我为你做了这个
You're the real champ around here. I made this for you.
好漂亮
Beautiful!
我们去喝啤酒  好吗?
Let's put our teeth around a few brews,okay?
- 我想找人陪陪  - 好主意
- I could use the company. - Good idea.
- 我必须和保罗叔叔出去吗?  - 如果我可以看电视的话
- Should I go out with Uncle Paulie? - If I can watch TV.
好的  听着
Okay. Listen.
你可以看电视  但是别太晚睡
You can watch TV,but don't stay up too late.
- 让骨头好好增长  - 好吧
- You gotta get them bones growin'. - All right.
比赛真精彩
What a fight. It was somethin'.
真精彩
Somethin'.
我早说过  除了你  你什么都能给他
I told you you could give him everything but you.
你就是没法给他你的心
You can't give him your heart.
无所谓  艾莉  真的
It's okay,really.
真的  我没事
Yeah. It's all right.
嘿  孩子  别太晚睡  好吗?
Kid,don't stay up too late,okay?
那场比赛真精彩
That was some fight.
你没事吧?
Are you okay?
没事
Sure.
我不会待太晚
I won't be out too late.
待会见  小拳王
See you,champ.
对了  和保罗好好去玩
Have a good time with Uncle Paulie.
女士们  先生们  让我介绍
Ladies and gentlemen,let me present the newest...
拳击史上最年轻的重量级拳王
the youngest heavyweight champion of all time...
汤米·"机关枪"
Tommy "The Machine" Gunn!
你认为这场比赛太容易吗?
Was the fight too easy?
他打了我几拳  不过我没受伤
He gave me a few good shots,but I was never hurt.
很高兴我当上拳王
I'm just glad to be the champ!
你不觉得根本不像冠军赛
Don't you think this looked more like a sparring session...
反而像练拳吗?
instead of a championship match?
- 你根本不费吹灰之力  - 你观察很敏锐
- Didn't look like you broke a sweat. - Very observant.
肯恩身体不适  就算肯恩没生病
Union Cane wasn't feelin' good,but Tommy would've done the same thing...
汤米一样能战胜他
if Union was 100 percent!
他打起来连吃奶的力气都没有
One hundred percent? He fought like he didn't have a heartbeat!
- 我们都知道肯恩是纸老虎  - 你说这句话是什么意思?
- Cane is just a paper champion. - What do you mean?
他的头衔是捏造的  他从未击败过洛奇
Cane's title was manufactured. He never won it from Balboa.
尤尼·肯恩是货真价实的
Get aboard. Union Cane is for real.
你能走出洛奇的阴影吗?
Think you'll ever get out from Rocky Balboa's shadow?
- 我赢了  还要我怎样?  - 我来告诉你
- I won the title! What more must I do? - I'll tell you.
- 你得找真正的对手才行  - 我今晚了打败拳王
- You've got to fight real opponents. - I beat the best tonight.
拳王? 那窝囊废根本不配
The best? This guy's a bum. He doesn't deserve a shot at the title.
各位  我们扯太远了
Gentlemen,whoa. We're getting carried away.
肯恩是公认的拳王  下一个问题
Union Cane was the recognized champ. Next question.
我们知道成绩是可以幕后操纵的
We know the rating system can be manipulated.
结论就是汤米击败一个二流选手
The bottom line is,Tommy Gunn beat a second-rate fighter...
他嘴里的玻璃可以作盏吊灯
with so much glass in his jaw he ought to be a chandelier.
他会证明自己是个拳王
Say what you want,but this man will prove to be a great champion.
他可能会赢几场比赛  但是绝不可能击败洛奇
He might win a few fights,but a Rocky Balboa he'll never be.
他不是洛奇  洛奇只有一个
No,no,he's no Rocky Balboa. There's only one Balboa.
洛奇才是真正的拳王
Balboa was a true people's champion.
汤米很快便能取代他的地位  下一个问题
But in time,Tommy Gunn may be able to fill his shoes. Next question.
- 别找肯恩这种三流货色  - 我会出战任何人  任何时间
- Not fighting stiffs like Cane! - I'll fight anybody,anywhere.
谁?  你何时才要打真正的拳赛?
Who? When? When you gonna fight a real fight?
各位  好了  谢谢大驾光临  下次再见
Gentlemen,come on. Thank you for coming tonight. We look forward to seeing you.
汤米  我有个建议
Tommy,I got something for you.
下一场何不跟红发妞打好了?
For your next fight,why not fight the redhead in the front row?
我听说她价码很低  怎么样?
I hear she comes real cheap. What about that?
我们下一场比赛再见
We look forward to seeing you at Tommy Gunn's next fight.
你为什么说洛奇比较强?  你也这么想吗?
Why did you say Balboa was better? Do you believe he's better?
你才是冠军
You champ! You champ!
汤米  你下一场跟谁比赛?
Who you gonna fight for the next fight,Tommy?
刚才是怎么回事?
What the hell happened in there?
我赢了还被他们讥笑为蹩脚货
I won the title and these people think I'm a bum!
- 你为何不支持我?  - 记者说的没错
- Why didn't you take up for me? - When the press is right,they're right.
我和洛奇一样行  我不在乎他们说什么
I'm as good as Balboa ever was! I don't give a damn what they say!
我厌倦被人称为机器人
I'm tired of being called a robot,too!
你斗不过新闻界  我也斗不过
You can't fight the press! I can't fight the press!
只要他们无法忘怀洛奇 他永远都是拳王
As long as they've got Balboa on the brain,he'll always be champ.
他纵横拳击场一生
The man fought wars in the ring.
你只是他的影子  没办法走出去
You're in his shadow with no way out.
- 连你自己都这么说  - 不  听好
- Listen to your own man talking. - No,no. Listen to me.
我有办法让你得到尊敬
There's a way to get the respect you deserve...
你必须要挑战洛奇
but you've got to challenge Balboa to fight man to man.
乔治可以在海外安排这场比赛
George could set this fight up abroad in weeks.
这将是有史以来最伟大的拳赛
It'd be the greatest fight ever.
老师对抗学生  老拳王对抗新拳王
Teacher against student. Old lion against young lion.
相信我  只有这么做才能心安
It's the only way you'll get peace of mind. Believe me when I tell you...
否则新闻界会一辈子  拿你与洛奇作文章
that press will hound you with that man's legend...
只要你还打拳的话
for as long as you wear boxing gloves.
你一定要挑战他
You gotta get him into that ring...
否则一辈子都要面对同样问题
or you'll be hearing questions like tonight for the rest of your life.
你会问自己  我能击败他吗?
Then you'll start to ask yourself,"Could I take him?
我真的够好吗?  人们真以为我只是复制品吗?
Am I good enough? Do people think I'm a cheap carbon copy...
还是因为肤色 才有机会的二流货色
or a second-rate pretender who only got a shot because of my skin tone?"
你一定要向他挑战
Got to challenge that man to fight,Tommy Gunn.
如果他拒绝  你就羞辱他  咄咄逼人  践踏他的自尊
And if he refuses,you've got to insult him! Dog him! Humiliate him!
用尽一切手段逼他上场
Do whatever you've got to do to get him into that ring...
你非这么做不可
but that's what you've got to do!
好  开球
Okay,blast off.
银球滚动  下去了
Rollin' silver. And now...
安迪  挡球杆坏了
Wait a minute! The flippers ain't flippin'! Andy!
- 那机器花了我不少钱  - 我也花了不少钱
- That machine cost me a fortune. - It's costin' me a fortune,too.
- 洛奇·巴尔博亚   - 是谁在鬼叫?
- Rocky Balboa! - What was that?
洛奇  外面有个人有话对你说
Rocky Balboa,there's a man out here wishing to speak with you.
你知道是谁吧?
You know who that is?
对  我知道是谁
Yeah,I know who that is.
洛奇  需要帮忙吗?
Rocky,need some help?
不用  又不是大食客比赛
No,guys. This ain't no pie eating contest.
你看  瞧瞧街上是谁
Look what's in the street.
你来这里干嘛?  你应该去开庆功宴
Tommy,what are you doin' here? You ought to be out celebrating.
我向你挑战  任何时间地点都行
I'm challenging you to a fight anytime,anyplace,anywhere.
- 拳赛?  - 没错
- Fight? - That's right.
你带这些人来这里  问我想不想和你打拳?
You coming here with these people asking if I want to throw hands with you?
- 就只是为了这个? - 对
- Is that what this is about? - Yeah,that's it.
我不是别人的机器人或傀儡
And I'm nobody's robot! Nobody's boy!
你要接受挑战或你只是孬种?
You accept the challenge,or are you yellow?
他没水准  洛奇  算了
He has no class. Come on,Rock.
- 他没水准  - 他是蹩脚货
- He has no class! - He couldn't carry your shoes.
我真不敢相信这小子
I can't believe this guy.
保罗  不关他的事  想不想打撞球?
Paulie,it ain't him. You wanna shoot some eight ball?
我话还没说完
I ain't through talking with you!
我对你无话可说了
I ain't got no more to say to you.
我只希望你一切顺利
I just want good things for you.
- 你这么做只是为了钱  - 为了钱?
- You're only in this for the money! - Money?
我厌倦了活在你的阴影下  人们骂我是你的机器人
I'm tired of walking around in your shadow. People call me your robot.
汤米  你认为我是为了钱?
You thought I was in this for the money?
我们情同手足
We were supposed to be like brothers.
记得吗?  你不要被人耍了
You don't remember that? You got a deception going here.
这傢伙只是在利用你
This guy here was using you for the bait.
他想刺激我们俩拳头相向   你明白吗?
He wants to get you and me in the ring.
他才好大捞一票
He wants us to fight each other to make the money.
他根本不关心你我的生死
He don't care about you or me neither.
够了  少说空话  谈现实问题
Come on! Enough of the fantasy. Let's talk reality.
洛奇  你接受汤米的挑战吗?
Rocky Balboa,are you prepared to accept Tommy Gunn's challenge?
我随时都能击败你
I would've taken you anytime.
你知道吗  你只是一堆废物
You're a piece of garbage,you know that?
- 不关你的事  - 不关我的事?
- This ain't none of your business. - Ain't none of my business?
- 不关我的事?  - 算了
- None of my business? - Forget about it.
他为你费尽心血  把你放在他家人之上
The man spit blood for you. He put you ahead of his family.
你却带这帮鼠辈来羞辱他?
And you bring these rat bums around here and kill his dignity?
是洛奇给你机会的  他才是真正的冠军
Rocky made you your shot. He's the real champ.
你只不过是则笑话而已  快滚  免得我打烂你的脸
You're just a goddamn joke. Get out of here before I break...
保罗  你怎么了
Paulie! What's the matter with you?
你打他值得吗?
Break your hand on this bum,what are you worth then?
你还好吗?
You okay?
你当初不该收留他的
You should've left him on the street where you found him.
- 你给我出去  - 你给我出去
- Get off of me,man! - Get him out of here.
你打倒他  何不试试打倒我?
You knocked him down. Why don't you try knocking me down?
在拳击场  汤米只在拳击场上打  我们走吧
In the ring. Tommy Gunn only fights in the ring! Let's get out of here.
我的拳击场就在街上
My ring's outside.
是吗?  来吧
Yeah? Let's do it.
现场转播
Let's go live! Go live!
洛奇  好好修理他  他是废物
Take him quick. He's a punk.
洛奇只配在街上混  你可是职业拳击手
Balboa's a street fighter. You're a prizefighter!
- 别傻了  - 我不是属于你的
- Don't be a fool! - You don't own me!
- 我不属于你  不属于任何人  - 别激动
- You don't own me! Nobody does! - Take it easy
- 我要该有的尊敬  - 那就来争取
- I want my respect! - Come and get it.
- 他是个三流货 好好教训他一顿  - 来吧
- He's a bum! Take him out. - Come on,Rocky.
我爱你  你知道吗?
I loved you,man. Do you know that?
汤米  我们原本该情同手足的
You and me was supposed to be like this,Tommy.
你却翻脸无情
You blew it!
你
You...
运气好罢了
Lucky punch!
他只配在街上混  我告诉过你别在街上打
But he's a street fighter,and I told you never to fight a street fight.
走吧  快点
Let's get out of here. Come on.
洛奇  你永远都是拳王
You're always the champ,Rocky.
太棒了  好题材
This is great stuff! Beautiful!
- 爸上电视了  他在打拳   - 什么?
- It's Dad! He's on TV! He's fighting. - What?
来  快出手
Come on,man!
洛奇  现在谁才是傀儡?
Balboa,who's your puppet now?
- 你一定要起来  - 站起来
- You gotta get up. - Get up!
你输了
You're out!
该死的就去死
If he dies,he dies.
你是拳王  起来再打一回合
You're the champ. Get up. One more round.
站起来  别放弃  努力奋战
Get up! Don't lay down! Fight hard!
他不是机器  我没听见钟声
He's no machine. I didn't hear no bell!
起来  你这个混蛋  米克爱你
Get up,you son of a bitch! Mickey loves you.
我没听见钟声响起
I didn't hear no bell.
再一回合
One more round.
汤米  回来  你大可不必
Tommy,get back. You don't need this.
- 你要是输就完蛋了  - 我还有一回合  来吧
- You lose,you're finished. - I got one more round. Come on.
这次我不要击倒你 我要打得你满街爬
I'm not gonna knock you out this time. I'm gonna put you to the street.
再一回合
One more round.
洛奇  加油
Come on,Rocky! Come on,Rock!
来吧  汤米  快出拳
Come on,get it!
你敢碰我  我就告你
Touch me and I'll sue.
你这是干什么?  快起来
What in the hell you doin'? Get up!
打死那个混蛋  他夺走了我的机会
Knock that bum out! He took my room!
刺拳  快出拳
Jab!Jab!
你快输光了
You're losing everything!
爸  你能打赢他
Come on,Dad. You can beat him!
快还击  你这个窝囊废
Fight back,you bum!
爸  加油
Dad,go for it!
揍他
Go for it!
艾莉  你说得对
Adrian,you were right.
该死
Goddamn!
只有美国才会发生
Only in America.
洛奇  你击败了那个蹩脚货?
Hey,Rock. You outclassed the bum,huh?
洛奇  不要
Come on,don't.
你敢碰我  我就告你
Touch me and I'll sue.
来吧  杂碎  敢碰我就告你
Come on,pug. Touch me and I'll sue.
告我什么?
Sue me for what?
神父
Yo,Father.
我就喜欢他这么做
I love it when he does that.
快点  我们快赶不上了
We're gonna be late.
快  飞毛腿
Come on,Speedy Gonzalez!
- 爸  你可以更棒的  - 不行了
- You can do better than that. - No way.
这些台阶好像越来越高  真要命
I don't know. These steps keep growing taller every year. My goodness!
孩子  你看这铜像
Look at this thing,kid.
只要铜像在  鸽子就有地方休息
As long as this thing is here,pigeons will always have a place to sit.
我真不敢相信  这里就是我起家的地方
I can't believe it. This is where it all started for me.
在台阶上来回奔跑
Running up and down these steps.
爸  我们要迟到了
Dad,we're gonna be late.
对  好的
Yeah,okay.
- 等一下  你耳朵怎么了?  - 有什么不对?
- What's wrong with your ear? - What's wrong with it?
你耳朵上有东西  肿起来了
You got something growing,like a bump.
什么肿起来?
What bump?
这个
This bump.
谢谢  爸
Thanks,Dad.
你应得的
Hey,you deserve it.
感谢上天赐你给我
Thank you for being born.
谢谢
Thank you,thank you.
你认为如何?  全新的我?
What do you think? The new me?
你就像我梦寐以求的女儿
Well,you look like the daughter that I always wanted.
你胡说什么?
What are you talkin' about?
别打我  我骨头快散了
Don't punch me. I'm gettin' brittle as it is.
你看看
Look at this.
我在这里跑步二十年了...
I've been running up and down these steps for 20 years...
竟从不知道馆内有名画
and I never knew there was valuable pictures in this building.
活到老学到老
You're never too old to learn something new.
你会爱死毕加索的
You're gonna love Picasso.
对  我什么人都爱
Yeah,well I love almost everybody.